<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cum bono Deo Raine from the clouds, vpon a choicke angel: or, A returned answere, to that common quæritur of our adversaries, VVhere was your church before Luther? Digested into several meditations, according to the difference of points. Extorted off the author, for stilling the vncessant, and no lesse clamorous coassation of some patmicke frogges, against the lawfulness of our calling.</title>
            <author>Logie, Andrew.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844465</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844465</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9280</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06199)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9280)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 844:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cum bono Deo Raine from the clouds, vpon a choicke angel: or, A returned answere, to that common quæritur of our adversaries, VVhere was your church before Luther? Digested into several meditations, according to the difference of points. Extorted off the author, for stilling the vncessant, and no lesse clamorous coassation of some patmicke frogges, against the lawfulness of our calling.</title>
                  <author>Logie, Andrew.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>77, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Edward Raban, dwelling vpon the market-place, at the Townes Armes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Aberdene :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Andrew Logie, Arch-Deane of Aberdene.</note>
                  <note>Following publication date: Cum privilegio.</note>
                  <note>With a final errata leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church --  Visibility --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> BONO DEO.</p>
            <p>RAINE FROM THE CLOVDS, vpon a Choicke Angel: OR, A returned Anſwere, to that common Quaeritur of our Adverſaries, <hi>VVhere was your Church before Luther?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Digeſted into ſeverall Meditations, according to the difference of Points.</p>
            <p>Extorted off the Author, for ſtilling the vnceſſant, and no leſſe clamorous Coaſſation of ſome Patmicke Frogges, <hi>againſt the lawfulneſſe of our Calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. XXI. VERS. 23. &amp;c.</hi>
               </bibl>
And when Hee was come into the Temple, the chiefe Prieſts, and Elders of the People, came vnto Him, as He was teaching, and ſayd; By what authoritie doeſt Thou theſe things? and who gaue Thee this authoritie?</q>
            <p>ABERDENE, IMPRINTED BY EDWARD RABAN, DWEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon the Market-place, at the Townes Armes, 1634. <hi>Cum privilegio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>BON ACCORD</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Inſignia Vrbis abredonie</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of Aberdeen</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, AND TRVELIE RELIGIOVS, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>ALEXANDER GORDON</hi> Of Clunie, Knight, <hi>Grace, Mercie, and Peace, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I haue dared, out of the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie (as vvee learne novv abuſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to ſpeake) to emprunt your Worſhips Name to this little vnpoliſhed piece of mine vnworthie workmanſhip; as juſtlie fearing to diſjoyne in my Dedication, whom GOD hath ſo happilie conjoyned in ſo tender and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affection: which your Worſhip ſhall giue as the trueth beareth, not to anie itching deſire on my part to put hand to the penne, as if <hi>in boc mustaceo quaererem laureolam;</hi> Nay, as who am more than loath and vnwilling of my ſelfe, to giue ought foorth to the publicke view, out of a conſciouſneſſe of my weakneſſe, whereof I am not the leaſt aſhamed to giue open ſignification; beſides diverſe others more than juſt reaſons and reſpects beſt knowne to my ſelfe: But to the inopportune importunitie of the Adverſarie, enforcing this taſke vpon mee, and expreſſing it of mee, how nilling ſo ever: As
<pb facs="tcp:9280:3"/>ſemblablie to that due regard had by mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rueth, (whereof it beſeemeth everie Gregarie Chriſtian in common to bee charie) though not the leaſt heere endangered of it ſelfe, and in it ſelfe; yet turning quaeſtionarie with ſome of the blacker note amongſt vs, as the eaſier, ſo as yet (bleſſed bee GOD for it) the beſt prey of our compaſſing Adverſaries; to whom wee envye not much theſe their ſo well accompliſhed Proſelytes. Certes, I haue not ſubſerved here my humor in this my Dedication, neither yet <hi>ſub manu demum hic mibi natum conſilium,</hi> as the triviall adage hath: But to ſpeake ſadlie, &amp; no leſſe ſincerelie, without the leaſt aſſentation, as which proves not much compatible with my naturall, if I durſt gloſe my ſelfe, not without right putation and due pondering of the matter, haue I recourſed with theſe my barelie &amp; nakedlie delineated, and vnfilled vp as yet lineaments, to the <hi>Zoar</hi> of your Worſhips Name; that ſhrouded and ſheltered vnder the ſhadowing winges of the ſame, they may finde the better harbouring at home, and receiue as the ſafer conduct, ſo the frier paſſage abroad: as who truelie here finde my ſelfe, as emboldened on everie hand, ſo neceſſitated on everie ſide; whether from that your Worſhips reſpectfull regard to all, and reverend eftimation of all of my Coate; or from that your Worſhips ſincere loue to the Trueth, (for the which wee haue mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to praiſe GOD, and pray for the happie and long continuance thereof, with a daylie increaſe, becauſe of this ſo thicke apoſtating Generation) from whence the meaneſt indevours of anie in this kynde cannot but finde moſt gracious acceptance, and heartie wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, at your Worſhips hands. Expecting and expeting your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips charitable conſtruction, to the better part of thoſe my ſimpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, or rude and homelie labours; and ſo bolde, as familiar vſage of your Worſhips Name, in full acquytall, of theſe whatſoever my paines, I moſt humbly take my leaue: this one thing intreating, what is wanting heere in the effect or worke it ſelfe, your Worſhip would bee pleaſed, out of that your <hi>Perſian</hi> mynde to arceſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat it from the workmans praepondering affection; and here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all moſt heartilie wiſhing your Worſhip the comble of all true hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, here and hence.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips in all obſequiouſneſſe, moſt humblie devoted,</hi> ANDREW LOGIE, <hi>Arch-Deane of</hi> ABERDENE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:3"/>
            <head>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THOR I.</head>
            <l>DIſsidium ſine diſsidio, ſine lite malignâ</l>
            <l>Cui lis &amp; bello qui ſine bella gerit,</l>
            <l>Militat ille DEO verè: velut umbra vagantur</l>
            <l>Qui ſecus hìc vires exſeruere ſuas.</l>
            <l>Iſta LOGI Tua laus. Nam dum Te oſtendis ìn armis,</l>
            <l>
               <abbr>Oppugnatque</abbr> novam Te duce Roma vetus,</l>
            <l>Dumque (aevi fatum!) velut unda ſupervenit undam</l>
            <l>Schiſmata ſchiſma parit, vulnera vulnus alit,</l>
            <l>Vſque ſacram puris manibus Tu tendis olivam,</l>
            <l>Vſque Tibi CHRISTI teſſera, PACIS AMOR.</l>
            <l>At nunc ô ſtrages! ô funera! ſanguine templi</l>
            <l>Non aditus, verum ipſa immaduere adyta.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. Wedderburnus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:4"/>
            <head>IN LAVDEM AVTHORIS.</head>
            <l>SAepius externis pugnans <hi>LOGIAEVS</hi> in oris</l>
            <l>Praevalidis rationum armis, <hi>Romana</hi> ſubegit</l>
            <l>Arma, <abbr>duceſque</abbr> ipſos: Patriis quoque victor in oris</l>
            <l>Exultat, <abbr>calcatque</abbr> hoſtes ratione, ſagaci</l>
            <l>Ingenio, <abbr>verboque</abbr> ſacro, flammantis Olympi</l>
            <l>Quod pater ipſe dedit. Telo hoc<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc enim nomine ſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignari vult <hi>Georgius Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taus,</hi> Romano Catholicus, Meletemata haec doctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Authori extorſit.</note> 
               <hi>Archangelus</hi> ipſe</l>
            <l>Confuſus periet; <abbr>
                  <hi>Romanorumque</hi>
               </abbr> phalanges,</l>
            <l>
               <abbr>Pontificemque</abbr> premet gladio hoc penetrante, ruinam</l>
            <l>Dogmatibus falſis feret hoc. <hi>LOGIAEVS;</hi> hic omnes</l>
            <l>Expediet nodos, quoſcunque vet <hi>Itala</hi> tellus</l>
            <l>Oppoſuit veris verbi praeconibus olim.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>To the Author.</head>
            <l>BRaue <hi>LOGIE,</hi> ſo continue to beate downe,</l>
            <l>By Scripture, Fathers, Reaſon, what is hatched</l>
            <l>Againſt the Trueth, by Doctors of new <hi>Rome:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And ſhow, that much of Vntrueths is but patched,</l>
            <l>Which they maintaine. So Trueth ſhall Thee vp-holde,</l>
            <l>And make Thy foes to quaile, but Thee more bolde.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Amoris ergo poſuit Cargillus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>MELETEMATA</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Quibus aſeritur Vocatio noſtrorum ab Adverſariorum velſyco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantiis quibuſcunque.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here came to mine hands ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtraying leafe, with the loynes truſſed, carrying or bearing this inſcription; <hi>Who want lawfull calling, are Robbers, according to the way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rands following, &amp;c.</hi> ſecunded and excepted by a farrage of rudelie conſarcinated, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedlie amaſſed paſſages of Scripture: needleſlie to proue the neceſſitie of Calling; as which is not ſo much as contraverted amongſt vs.</p>
            <p>Truelie wee admit this leſlaean, as leſſe indeede lying po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, <hi>vel. ultro;</hi> as who acknowledge in common, <hi>Quòd nemo debeat</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>or,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Miniſterium invadere:</hi> That none muſt take this honour to himſelfe,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.4.</note> but hee who is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led as <hi>Aaron.</hi> Where in the verie entrie wee would headilie diſtinguiſh betwixt theſe two, To deferre our travels to the Church; and, To obtrude them on the Church, and intrude our ſelues into the Church: for the firſt may be lawfull in caſes through the iniquitie of tyme, <hi>Vbi non virtus aut meritum, ſed favor ereat preſbyterum:</hi> but this laſt remaineth ſtill vnlawfull. It holdeth alwayes true, that in a Miniſter there is required, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or facultie to teach; (for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt not bee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9280:5"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> would bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:) ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>poteſtas,</hi> as they ſpeake in Schooles; hee muſt bee inſtructed with commiſſion. Hitherto the LORD is ſaid to haue called <hi>Bezaleel</hi> by name, and to haue filled him with his ſpirit for working in his Tabernacle, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. Hitherto the LORD commanded <hi>Moſes,</hi> to take <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nun,</hi> in whom the ſpirit was, and to put hands vpon him, <hi>Num.</hi> 27. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. Hither-to wee ſee, <hi>Numbers,</hi> 17. amongſt all the twelue Roddes of the Princes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> onelie AARONS Rodde to haue budded, bloſſomed, and borne rype Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondes; where-by wee are taught ſymbolicallie, that the LORD will onelie bleſſe their Miniſtrie, whom hee ſetteth aworke himſelfe.<note place="margin">Matth. 28.19.</note> Hitherto wee ſee the marriage of theſe three <hi>in unum Spiritum, Ite, Docete, Baptizate, Matthew.</hi> the laſt at the vpſhot, whereas CHRIST ſent foorth his Diſciples to that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Miniſtrie. Hitherto wee ſee with what care the whole Prophets, at leaſt in common, alleadged ſtill in the entrie of their propheſie to their warrand of Calling. Yea, laſt wee ſee, <hi>quàm ſeverè à</hi> DEO <hi>hic animadverſum in ſacri bujus ordinis teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratores,</hi> but the leaſt regard to their qualitie. But in reſpect our Adverſarie goeth no farther length, but contenteth him ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie to amaſſe ſome paſſages together, enforcing the neceſſitie of Vocation or Calling, I might <hi>vel citra tenuiſsimum pulviſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum hoc labore defungi,</hi> by ſubſcrybing to this granted and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged trueth in common: the quaeſtion ſtill remaining, with whom this vocation or calling is. Alwayes I ſhall lay hold on the matter even from ſo farre, and impoſe here a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie on my ſelfe, whereas there is none ſo much as deferred, or but barelie offered; not out of the leaſt conſciouſneſſe of anie vnlawfulneſſe of our Calling, or the leaſt weakneſſe therein; Neither yet heerein ſillilie to ſubſerue the humour of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſarie; Neither yet out of the leaſt praeſumption on my part: but <hi>fiduciâ bonae cauſae;</hi> as lykewiſe to ſatiſfie, in ſome meaſure, as the expectation of all, ſo the moſt earneſt expetition of the well affected: as laſt of all, leſt elſe I might juſtlie ſeeme, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing it with a dry foote, to overleape it lyke a Ditch, from whence I feared danger: Yea, and bee miſconſtrued, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trect the Combate, whiles being ſo pointlie poynted at, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:9280:5"/>Out of theſe conſiderations then, one word, <hi>en paſſant,</hi> with a running pen, of this ſo much ventilated quaeſtion, of our Church her being before <hi>Luther;</hi> which our Adverſaries with ſo ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; full mouth noyſe ſo much to day, yea, fill both Heaven and Earth with the brute hereof, and wherein they place the ſtrength of their cauſe, as <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength lay in his haire. Truelie, to vntye and vnlooſe this their Gordian knot, <hi>non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectandus hîc nobis Elias aliquis, aut</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Primum Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt of all, this maine ground would be laide, and headilie adverted vnto, in the Frontiſpice of this Worke: to wit, That the Church is ſtill one and the ſame, though not alwayes alyke affected; as a man remaineth one and the ſelfe ſame man in ſickneſſe and health. Now from hence the ridiculous follie of theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of our Adverſaries appeare of will: to wit, Of the being of our Church before LVTHER; as lykewyſe, If ſhee was in Poprie or not. Certes, <hi>Papatus invaſit Eccleſiam,</hi> Poprie hath invaded the Church: for <hi>accidentis eſt ineſſe ſubjecto,</hi> but not on the contrarie, <hi>ſubjecti ineſſe ſuo accidenti:</hi> ſo that the Church throughout her diverſe conditions, before Poprie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Poprie, and delivered, or come foorth of <hi>Babel,</hi> is but one
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9280:6"/>and the ſame, remaining thus one common ſubject, lyable to diverſe alterations; and lyke heerein to the naturall or phyſicall bodie of man, diverſlie affected. Hitherto it is that you ſee the two witneſſes, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.3. to bee cloathed in ſacke-cloath, <hi>ob triſtem, videlicet, Eccleſiae ſtatum;</hi> and againe, the Angels com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming foorth with the ſeaven Plagues, <hi>ad ſumendum debitas de Antichriſto poenas,</hi> to be cloathed, in ſigne of victorie &amp; triumph, ſutablie in pure bright linnen, <hi>Revel.</hi> 15. <hi>ob laetum Eccleſiae ſtatum:</hi> Now <hi>Eſt</hi> of the third adjacent, praeſupponeth <hi>Eſt</hi> of the ſecond, as they ſpeake in Schooles: And ſo it remaineth <hi>quòd ſubinde alia, atque alia ſit Eccleſiae facies.</hi> Whitherto ſhee is well likened by the Fathers to the Moone, which remaineth one and the ſame, <hi>etiam vel ubi patitur deliquium,</hi> even while ſhee is eclipſed. For cloſure then, as the Church remained the ſame even whilſt holden in captivitie in that Eaſterne <hi>Babylon;</hi> ſo did ſhee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine one and the ſame, whilſt thralled and enbondaged in that Weſterne and myſticall <hi>Babylon,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Secundum Meletema.</head>
               <p>WEE acknowledge all in common, the Church for the ground and Pillar of the Trueth; the word Pillar heere being taken aright, <hi>ratione, ſcilicet, forenſi,</hi> and not <hi>Architectonicâ</hi> (for elſe all ſhoud proue confuſed in that ſpeach of Sainct <hi>Paules;</hi> as if <hi>domus, &amp; id eui innititur do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:9280:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>that is, the Trueth and the Church were one and the ſame, as our Adverſaries heere confound: yea, as if the Church were not built on that foundation of the Prophets, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles their doctrine) as lykewyſe alluſion heere being made, <hi>ad domum illam Salomonis totam columnis conſpicuam.</hi> I leaue to ſpeake of the different interpunction, which as it would cleare all heere, ſo hath it no little probabilitie, becauſe of the ſynap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke or copulatiue particle, <hi>Kaì,</hi> in the beginning of the next verſe, which would ſeeme to knit theſe wordes with ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing going before, to this ſenſe; That CHRIST, or GOD, manifeſted in the fleſh, is the ground and pillar of the Trueth, &amp; without controverſie the great myſterie of godlineſſe. But to follow the received interpunction &amp; interpretation, <hi>ne crabrones irritemus,</hi> it is cleare fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence, that we muſt needs acknowledge that pillar for the Church, wherevpon wee find the Trueth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, ſince that, <hi>ad Eccleſiam, tanquam ad columnam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat veritas; in ea demum comparet;</hi> ſo that from the doctrine, judgement muſt bee given of the Church, and not on the contrarie. Whitherto <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> ſayeth well, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Wherefore thus are wee ledde by the hand to inſtitute a tryall, <hi>penes quod ſit veritas,</hi> where and with whom the Trueth is; this proveth in the ende the laſt analyſis or reſolution of this quaeſtion. If I durſt make bolde, I would poſe our Adverſaries heere a little of their judgement, Whether it bee ſafer and ſurer worke, with <hi>Tertullian, perſonas ex fide,</hi> or on the contrarie, <hi>fidem ex perſonis aeſtimare:</hi> now our Adverſaries holde this latter, and ſo muſt. needes promiſcuouſlie receiue the leaven of the Phariſees, becauſe they ſit in MOSES Chaire, for ſound and true Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. That I may make this farther tributarie to the errand in hand, from hence I thus argue demonſtratiuelie:</p>
               <p>That Trueth which CHRIST and his Apoſtles taught, wanted never men in all Ages conſtantlie to profeſſe the ſame: (for the Trueth could never want witneſſes)</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9280:7"/>But ſo it is, that which wee holde and teach, is one and the ſame with that Trueth which CHRIST and his Apoſtles taught.</p>
               <p>Ergo, This our doctrine wanted never men in all Ages to profeſſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thus wee bring our Adverſaries from the hiſtoricall part, to the doctrinall. Alwayes, leſt I ſhould ſeeme heere to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline this other part, I muſt ſpeake a little heereof. Truelie, <hi>pudendam &amp; ſtupendam prodit bîc</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hee bewrayeth a groſſe and inexpiable aniſtoreſie, who denyeth, that there were not ſtill more <hi>Chriſtiani,</hi> ſo to ſpeake in oppoſition, than <hi>Papani,</hi> more not acknowledging the Pope, and his authoritie, than adhering to him, even before LVTHER, and detection of Poprie by him, throughout the world, as were eaſie to proue by induction. It is cleare, <hi>ex Pauli veneti navigationibus orientalibus,</hi> that there were moſt frequent Chriſtian Churches in thoſe dayes wherein hee wrote, ſome three or foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth yeares ſince, as <hi>apud Indos, ultra &amp; cis Gangen.</hi> Amongſt the <hi>Tartars</hi> or <hi>Tatars,</hi> in <hi>Scythia, In utraque Armenia, in Meſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potamia,</hi> beſides diverſe other places. Now the greater part of all theſe Chriſtians ſcarſe vnderſtood ſo much as by heare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, of the bare and naked name of the Pope. Againe, in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia,</hi> the large and ample extent of the <hi>Abyſsin</hi> Churches is knowne: where if wee ſhould bee pleaſed to meaſure the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent but of thoſe Provinces, wee ſhould finde even thoſe alone to exceede farre all thoſe which in <hi>Europe</hi> acknowledge his holineſſe, for-ſooth. Further, <hi>ſi adhuc libeat &amp; ad ſeptentrionem exeurrere,</hi> we ſhall find moſt largelie diffuſed Churches, as <hi>Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum, Ruthenorum, Ruſſorum;</hi> yea, yet <hi>intra mare Caspium,</hi> wee ſhall ſinde many Churches over which the Pope hath not the leaſt power. But that wee may doe <hi>etiam ſupra id quod rogatur;</hi> the <hi>Europaean Graecians</hi> doe no leſſe execrate the Pope, than wee doe. They excommunicate him yearelie, they inſtile him in common, with vs, by the name of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> I would learne of our Adverſaries, what they can ſay <hi>de Anglis, quid de Bobemis,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9280:7"/>quid de Valdenſibus, Albigenſibus,</hi> of the <hi>Wallons</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who being diſperſed diverſlie throughout <hi>Europe, proſeminarunt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem dogmata,</hi> ſew the ſame doctrine which <hi>Hus,</hi> and before him, <hi>Wicleff,</hi> and after both theſe, LVTHER but renewed. If wee ſhould bee pleaſed to repeat and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceſſe the Hiſtories but of theſe <hi>Europaean Chriſtians,</hi> out of our Adverſaries their owne Monuments, who wrote againſt them in thoſe tymes, wee ſhall finde the moſt approved Writers amongſt them, <hi>eadem ipſis dogmata pro erroribus impingere,</hi> to lay the ſame Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maes or pointes to their charge for errours, which wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and ſuſtaine to day for true Dogmaes, and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Chriſtian Fayth. As for taſte; That the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> had overwhelmed by the multitude of his Traditions, as by a deludge, the whole Chriſtian Church. Item, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatorie Sacrifices for the quicke and the dead were null; That there was no Purgatorie; No merit of works; beſides diverſe other pointes which they denyed, as, Nundination of Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Yea, and whereas amongſt the reſt of their Articles of the Popiſh Fayth, this obtained, <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendum Imperatorem non immediatè à</hi> DEO, <hi>ſed à Papa poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem accepiſſe;</hi> That it was to bee holden, that the Emperour had not, or helde not his power immediatelie from GOD, but from the Pope and his holineſſe, for-ſooth; and that theſe who thought otherwayes, were to bee ranked amongſt the <hi>Manichaeans,</hi> as who thus eſtabliſhed two Principles. It is more than notoriouſly heere knowne, <hi>quam acriter inſectati hîc Albigenſes,</hi> how odiouſlie they traduced them, <hi>etiam hoc nomine, multis ad hoc ridiculis &amp; contumelioſis ad ludibrium confictis nominibus,</hi> as is cleare out of the Edicts of <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſecond Emperour: as now calling them, by the name of <hi>Ioſephytes,</hi> now of <hi>Turripines,</hi> now of <hi>Picards,</hi> now of <hi>Lombards,</hi> now of <hi>Tatars,</hi> as it were voyaging men, to wit, from the places through the which they were diverſlie diſperſed; yea, at laſt, <hi>(ne quid hîc deeſſet)</hi> by the name of <hi>Manichaeans.</hi> Now you ſee the traduction of our Church, at leaſt <hi>per tempus, tempora, &amp; dimidium temporis:</hi> for three hundreth and fiftie years, and even ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9280:8"/>long before <hi>Hus, Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague;</hi> yea, or <hi>Wickleff,</hi> let bee LVTHER. <hi>Catalogus teſtium veritatis</hi> ſhoweth, <hi>ah omni aevo reclamatum doctrinae Pontificiae;</hi> and pointeth deicticallie at thoſe who oppoſed and oppugned the ſame, and ſtood for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie trueth. Nay, let vs but evolue and turne over their Monuments, and wee ſhall finde ſtore of thoſe who long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore LVTHER, diverſe ages, not onelie ſet themſelues againſt that Antichriſtian doctrine; but ſuffered for this their oppoſition moſt exquiſite torments: and quaeſtionleſſe wee ſhould haue had yet farre greater ſtore of ſuch examples, <hi>niſi hiſtoriarum cuſtodia penes ipſos fuiſſet, &amp; ſic partus Iſraeliticos vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis werſiſſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To winde vp this point: Could this their Church bee then the ſole, and the Catholicke Church? <hi>Vincentius Lyrinenſis</hi> defineth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>quod ſemper, quod ubique, quod ab omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> Now from this my hiſtoricall deduction, it is cleare, that Poprie cannot bee ſayde to bee ſuch; for it obtained not alwayes: for <hi>non ab initio,</hi> though it began well tymouſlie to bee aworking in the verie Apoſtles their dayes, albeit well imperceptibly, according to the nature of a myſterie; it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained not everie where, nor amongſt all, &amp;c. Nay, you may ſee from this my diſcourſe, that it was ſo farre from being ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie Catholicke, as that it was not ſo much as ſuch, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, or compariſon, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:9280:8"/>
               <head>Tertium Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>EE thinkes it ſtrange, how our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries can vrge the viſibilitie of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church: for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> incurreth not in the ſenſe, <hi>Mente non ſenſu depraehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, percipitur: ſenſus quippe eſt ſingularium.</hi> Againe, the Catholicke Church is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Fayth: Now <hi>Fides eſt</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an evidence of thinges not ſeene, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſayeth, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1: and as Sainct AVGVSTINE ſayeth, <hi>Si vides, non eſt fides.</hi> Whitherto BELLARMINE is driven thus to pronounce heere, <hi>De Eccleſia, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Melius dico in Eccleſia aliquid videri, &amp; aliquid credi: videmus enim eum coetum qui eſt Eccleſia, ſed quod ille coetus ſit Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, hoc non videmus, ſed credimus,</hi> &amp;c. Thus to trace heere but our Adverſarie, <hi>Nihil Eccleſiae formale, aut Eccleſiae, qua talis, conſtitutivum, vel ipſo hic nobis ſuffragante, aſtipulante, eſt viſibile aut ſenſui expoſitum.</hi> The Catholicke Church conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of CHRIST the Head, of the Church triumphing in Heaven, and of this Way-faring and Warre-faring on Earth. Now, who can ſuſtaine to affirme this Church to bee viſible? I grant, that the matter prooveth eaſier with our Adverſaries, who haue CHRIST with them bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſtill preſent in the Hoſtie, for-ſooth, vpon the Prieſtes intention; and the Sainctes and Angles ſemblablie in their
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9280:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>repreſenting Images. Nay, to deale heere well liberallie with our Adverſaries, and giue them, that, that which is but the moſt ignoble part of the Church, which <hi>repit</hi> or <hi>ſerpit humi,</hi> which is but a edolating, exaſciating, effigia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or efforming heere but by piece-maile, may bee called by the name of the Catholicke Church. I pray you, may all theſe particular Churches, ſo diverſlie diſperſed throughout the whole world, gathered of every Trybe, Nation, Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Language, bee together, and at once pointed at by finger? for it is headilie to bee obſerved, how our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries confound in this argument, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>viſibile,</hi> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>videri;</hi> taking <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>viſibile, non de potentia, ſed de actu, &amp;c.</hi> As to that their Palmarie, or maine Argument heere, <hi>Quod, cujus par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes omnes ſunt viſibles, &amp; ipſum totum tale ſit;</hi> and ſo that the Catholicke Church muſt needs bee viſible, becauſe of the viſibilitie of all the particulare Churches. Truelie this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>non tam habet paralogiſmum, quam ſapit, redolet hellebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmum;</hi> as if all the particulare Churches throughout the world, <hi>Locorum intervallis tam diſsitae, ſimul &amp; ſemel digito notari poſſent.</hi> But to binde our Adverſaries heere, I argue thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod deſideratur vel in toto Phyſico, illud frustra requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur, malè exigitur in to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o mystico:</hi> That is, What is found wanting, or is not findable in a phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bodie, is ill required and ſought for in a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall.</p>
               <p>But ſo it is, <hi>vel in toto Phyſico,</hi> even in a Phyſicall bodie, <hi>quantitatis, ſcilicet, ita diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae, ut partes longiſsimis locorum intervallis à ſein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicem distent, partes omnes ſimul &amp; ſemel digito notari non poſſunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ergo, farre leſſe is this findable in a myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die; yea, in ſuch a bodie, <hi>quod ſimul &amp; continuum &amp; diſcretum praedicatur eſſe in Scripturis;</hi> as which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the names of things, <hi>quantitatis utriuſque, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuae &amp; diſcretae,</hi> as of an Houſe, of a Flocke, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:9280:9"/>I leaue to ſhow, How the Church may bee called viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and inviſible, in different regards, <hi>respectis</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>materialis,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>formalis; reſpectu formae internae,</hi> or <hi>externae;</hi> which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall forme againe, <hi>variis mutationum vicibus ac gyris obnoxia, ac infesta est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Quartum Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F ſo bee, That the Church may ſuffer ſuch eclipſe, as to her externall forme or viſible face, as that ſhee cannot bee eſpyed, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, there remaining but a remanent through the election of Grace; then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that this demand of our Adverſaries, Concerning the being of our Church before LVTHER, as to that her externall forme, or viſible face, is but idle. But wee may ſee the poſſibilitie of this hypotheſe vnder both the Teſtamentes: in the dayes of <hi>Eli,</hi> vnder the olde Teſtament, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 19; and in Sainct <hi>Pauls</hi> time, vnder the newe Covenant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. Then the queſtion turneth to this, to ſee, When and where this caſe hath behappened the Church: wherefore, from hence thus I reaſon:</p>
               <p>In the dayes of <hi>Eliah,</hi> there was a true Church in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which the LORDS owne anſwere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9280:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>to <hi>Eliah</hi> vpon that his complaint, inſtructeth to the full: except that ſeaven thouſand, <hi>Nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus definitus pro indefinito,</hi> can not make vp a Church with our Adverſaries heere, who can cut her ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at tymes to their owne advantage, as in their private Communion:</p>
               <p>But ſo it is, this Church ſuffered eclipſe, as to her outward forme, or viſible face: for howe could ſhee elſe haue eſcaped even the ſight of the Prophet, <hi>cui erant &amp; ad videndum oculi?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ergo, a Church ceaſeth not to bee ſimplie, whilſt eclipſed as to her externall forme, or viſible face.</p>
               <p>Thus you may perceiue evidentlie, how our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries heere deceiue the ſimpler ſort, vrging ſtill the viſib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the Church: for what hath alreadie behappened the Church, the ſame caſe may againe befall her; and ſo their quaeſtion reſolveth in the winde.</p>
               <p>Our Adverſaries heere perceiving and feeling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſtraited, as touching the Church in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to bethinke with themſelues of ſome eſcape here, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto to haue their refuge; wherefore they grant this to bee true of the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or of <hi>Samaria:</hi> but they pretende, that there was then a flowriſhing Church in <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> vnder the reigne of <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Ioſaphat,</hi> godlie Princes; and ſo that this inſtance proveth nothing for the whole Church vnder the Law.</p>
               <p>For anſwere: Firſt, wee alleadge not hitherto that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that therevpon wee may conclude the generall, or in the generall, of the whole ancient Church vnder the Law; but onlie to proue, that theſe may ſuffer, yea, and haue <hi>reapſe</hi> ſuffered divorce: that is, That a Church may remaine ſimplie a Church, though eclipſed, as to her ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9280:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>policie, outward forme, or viſible face; which our Adverſaries flatlie deny, becauſe of the errand in hand.</p>
               <p>Next: it is ſufficient for probation of our Theme, and decyding the quaeſtion betwixt them and vs, to prooue this of anie particular Church: for why may not the ſame caſe befall anie ſiſter Church? So <hi>frustra ſunt Adverſarii;</hi> whereas they except, that this alleadged inſtance by vs prooveth nothing for the Catholicke Church, or for the whole Church vnder the Law: for wee are not ſo ſwollen vp, as to acclaime to vs the name of the Catholicke Church, but humblie acknowledge our ſelues but Daughters of that Mother.</p>
               <p>Laſt, <hi>ut dejiciamus eos hoc praeſidio,</hi> that wee may driue them from this ſtarting hole; I would poſe our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, if the Church of <hi>Iudah</hi> had anie farther Priviledge heere. Truelie, wee may ſee <hi>Iudah</hi> to haue ſurpaſſed her Siſter <hi>Samaria</hi> in her abhominations; nay, to haue exceeded <hi>Sodome,</hi> and her daughters, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16. yea, wee finde her revolts ſo generall, as that Prince, Prieſt, and People, all in common, abandoned the Law of GOD, declined from His ſervice, fell away to Idolatrie, and followed after the ſame, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 7. <hi>verſ. ultino.</hi> But becauſe that generals can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not binde, nor worke with our Adverſaries, let vs inſtance the matter more particularlie. Whereas King <hi>Ahaz</hi> ſet vp a ſtrange Altar, after the faſhion of that of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> in the houſe of GOD; nay, the Prieſt himſelfe, <hi>Vriiah,</hi> made it, and ſet it vp at the wicked Kinges commaundement, and ſacrificed therevpon vnto the gods of the <hi>Damaſconians:</hi> yea, laſt, whereas this wicked King gathered together the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the Houſe of GOD, brake them, and ſhut vp the doores of the Houſe of the LORD, made him Altars in everie corner of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and in everie Citie of <hi>Iudah</hi> made high places, to burne Incenſe vnto other gods, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 16. <hi>Item</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. <hi>verſ.</hi> 23.24.25. I would poſe our Adverſaries heere, where was the viſible face of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9280:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church of <hi>Iudah,</hi> whilſt Idolatrie thus occupied, and filled the Temple; nay, filled everie corner, and everie high place? And becauſe <hi>una birundo non facit ver,</hi> I would inquire yet farther, Where was the viſible Church of <hi>Iudah,</hi> whereas <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> reſtored Idolatrie, as lykewyſe vnder <hi>Amon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If our Adverſaries would except heere, That there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſtill a Church throughout all thoſe dayes and times, to wit, in ſome certaine perſons, as Prophets, and others of the ſame note, the anſwere ſhould prooue eaſie. The quaeſtion is not of the Church ſimplie, for there remaineth ſtill a Church, while there remaine anie two or three, <hi>qui Patrem in CHRISTO per Spiritum invocent;</hi> but of the Church, as to her externall policie, If ſhee remaine alwayes ſo viſible, as to her externall forme, as that ſhee may bee ſtraight diſcerned, or internoſced by the eye, from other companies, whether acclaiming or not acclaiming to them this name: for our Adverſaries cannot away, that anie Church receiue the name of a true Church, which is not inſtructed with this externall policie, furniſhed with this outward viſibilitie, eutaxie, and conſtitution.</p>
               <p>If you could bee pleaſed, heere to eye a little with mee the Church, throughout her whole marching, from Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to the Tabernacle, and from thence to the Temple; as lykewyſe throughout her whole eſtate, before the Law, vnder the Law, and vnder Grace; you ſhould ſee her ſtill to haue ſuffered eclipſes, and deliquies, as to her externall forme, or viſible face: ſo that our Adverſaries denying, That a Church can turne inviſible, <hi>quoad externam'</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>politiam,</hi> and yet continue a Church, bewray an inexpiable aniſtoreſie, or ignorance of the ſacred hiſtorie. Reade you not in the third Chapter of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> of the fall of our firſt Parents? and at the cloſure of the fourth Chapter, howe men began to call vpon the Name of the LORD, as <hi>Enoch</hi> was borne to <hi>Seth,</hi> which importeth a prior ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Religion? How long continued the true Religion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:9280:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnviolated, <hi>Etiam in ſanctâ illâ gente,</hi> even in that holie po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie of SHEM? Were not ABRAHAMS Fathers Idolaters? and himſelfe called out of VR of the CHAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAEANS, being an Idolater? Againe, Did not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple followe Idolatrie the ſpace of two hundreth yeares in AEGYPT, without ſo much as anie open oppoſite? <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel</hi> 23. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3. and 19. Heere both the Daughters, IV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAH as ISRAEL, or SAMARIA, idolatred, and committed Fornication, as is cleare from the alleadged place.</p>
               <p>What will our Adverſaries ſay heere, where the whole people idolatred, and worſhipped the golden Calfe, <hi>etiam</hi> ARAONE <hi>duce? Exod.</hi> 32. For as to that, That MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES was free heere, it is nothing: for hee is <hi>Eccleſiae,</hi> but <hi>non Eccleſia.</hi> BELLARMINE here affirmeth yet farther; That the whole Levites remained pure, and free from this contagion, becauſe that the whole ſonnes of LEVI are ſayde to haue gathered themſelues vnto him, <hi>Vbi ultionem pararet, poenas exigeret Idolomanias illius.</hi> For aunſwere, BEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LARMINE playeth the Sophiſt heere; for the Text ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to ſhow indeede who they were that adjoyned them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to MOSES, that they were Levites: but it ſayeth not, that the Levites were all to one pure, and free from this contagion; nay, it is not probable, that all the ſonnes of LEVI gathered themſelues to MOSES: for ſo, if <hi>omnes ſeſe ad ultionem accinxiſſent, majorem indubiè edidiſſent ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem:</hi> for a little after, <hi>Habito eorum cenſu,</hi> they are recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned foorth about nine thouſand. Alwayes the firſt anſwere ſerveth the turne. What can our Adverſaries ſay to their manifolde and moſt frequent revolts vnder the IVDGES? Nay, What can they poſſible except heere, whereas wee reade, <hi>Iudg. Cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27.33.34. of the generall revolt of the Iudge and people in common, whilſt even GIDEON, one of the Iudges, of no ſlender note, made an Ephod, and put it in EPHRATH his Citie, where all ISRAEL
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9280:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>went a-whoring after it: Yea, and not ſtaying heere; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death, went a-whoring after <hi>Baalim,</hi> and made <hi>Baal-Berith</hi> their god?</p>
               <p>By the waye heere it is obſerveable, what aunſwere that ARCHI-RABBI BELLARMINE, returneth to this exception of our men: to wit, Of the generall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing of the Prophets, againſt the generall defection of the whole bodie in common, of the whole people, head and tayle, as it were: to wit, That, that is directed to all, <hi>oratorio more,</hi> which pertayneth but to the greater part: that is, <hi>per</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Nowe then, to take but what hee giveth; it holdeth then ſtill true, <hi>Eccleſiam deficere ſaltem ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum rationem</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: or, in reſpect of the greater part, <hi>Aufugiente &amp; ſubducente ſe interim muliere in deſertum,</hi> the Woman taking her flight in the meane time to the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, <hi>ubi à DEO mirabiliter paſcitur, rationibus nobis ſaepe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultis, ſibi autem ut notiſsimis, ita facillimis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to come a little nearer: I would learne of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, Where the viſible face of the Church was, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as CHRIST came into the worlde; If this was to bee meaſured, <hi>ex viſibili illa Sacerdotum ſucceſsione,</hi> from that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſucceſſion of the Prieſtes? Againe, I would vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand heere, What ſhall bee the viſible, or externall forme, or face of the Church, whereas CHRIST ſhall come to judgement, whiles Hee hath fore-propheſied Himſelfe, Hee ſhall ſcarſe finde Fayth on the Earth? This I vrge onelie, <hi>ad ſenſum currentem.</hi> I grant indeede, that there may bee ſuch a viſible Church, as our Adverſaries require, and holde; to wit, As conſiſting of members devoyde of Fayth, Hope, and Charitie: for I would haue you to remember heere that of BELLARMINE, <hi>de Eccleſiae, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect. ultima,</hi> where hee ſayeth, <hi>Non requiri ad hoc ut quis ſit mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum Eccleſiae, ut habeat Fidem, Spem, Charitatem.</hi> And yet, <hi>Si diis placet,</hi> this Church ſhall bee <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Church reſted, as ſome of themſelues even acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9280:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the perſon of the bleſſed Virgine, where was then the viſible face of the Church?</p>
               <p>I would farther poſe our Adverſaries; If the Kingdome of GOD may not admit and ſuffer tranſlation, from one Nation to another: nay, and if it hath not indeede ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſame? What follie, or yet madneſſe is it then, ſo pertinaciouſlie to pretende heere, That a Church cannot ſuffer ſuch eclipſe, as to her externall forme, as that ſhee may not bee eſpyed? Wherefore, to deale a little more preſslie here, I would vnderſtand, if What hath behappened to anie one part of the Catholicke Church, that is, to this or that particular Church, may not befall another: or elſe, the reaſon of the difference heere: But ſo it is, This or that particular Church may ſuffer this eclipſe, yea, admit this tranſlation, as the Church of EPHESVS, to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it exemplarlie: for, <hi>Nonne CHRISTVS hoc ipſum interminatur in Epistolis ad Aſiaticas Eccleſias tollam Candelabrum?</hi> doeth hee not thus menace the Church of EPHESVS, <hi>Revel. Cap. 2. verſ. 5.</hi> that hee will come againſt her ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and remooue her Candle-ſticke out of his place, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſhee amende? Then it remayneth, That the lyke caſe may befall anie Church elſe.</p>
               <p>To vſe yet a fewe particulare inſtances, for the fuller and clearer conviction of our Adverſaries, <hi>Vbi Mahumetiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus omnia in Oriente obtinuit:</hi> nay, <hi>Vbi totus orbis ingemuit, &amp; ſeſe Arrianum factum eſſe, miratus eſt, ubi viſibilis illa Eccleſiae fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies quaeſo videris?</hi> Whereas <hi>Mahumetiſme</hi> obtayned through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Eaſt; nay, and the whole worlde groaned vnder the heavie Yoake, and Burden of <hi>Arrianiſme,</hi> vvhere was the viſible face of the Church?</p>
               <p>Truelie, there is nothing more certaine, than that there were manie moſt flowriſhing Churches in the Eaſt, which are to daye <hi>(proh dolor)</hi> transformed in <hi>Muſcetas Mahumetano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> Nay, I haue it of thoſe, who had it <hi>ex</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9280:13"/>they ſaw in <hi>Greece</hi> manie flowriſhing Cities, wherein there was not ſo much as the leaſt trace of anie Church, nor veſtige of anie Chriſtian doctrine: <hi>omnia quippe occupaverat Mahumetica colluvies.</hi> But leſt I might ſeeme heere, <hi>vel è ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu proferre testem,</hi> as is ordinarie with our Adverſaries, I ſticke not to deferre this to their owne teſtimonie, or the teſtimonie to themſelues. I pray you then, what letteth mee to reaſon heere, by way of Analogie, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That what hath behappened this or theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches, may befall others their Siſters, nothing more heere priviledged againſt the ſame danger?</p>
               <p>That wee may come yet nearer, and ſtrike home, let mee demande of our Adverſaries, Whether or not the Church vnder Grace ſhould haue her flight to the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that with Eagles wings, not onlie for pernicitie in flying, but for continuing of the flight, in reſpect of tract of tyme, and ſo lurke there for a goodlie ſpace? I hope our Adverſaries dare not ſo farre foorth rubbe their fore-heads heere, as openlie to diſavow this, the Scripture beeing heere ſo expreſſe and formall. Now, this beeing laide, the anſwere to the maine quaeſtion prooveth eaſie: Our Church was lurking in the Deſert, fleeing the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Dragon; as that Church of <hi>Iſrael</hi> lurked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that perſecution of <hi>Achab</hi> and <hi>Iezabel.</hi> Nay, this affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs an infallible demonſtration for vs, and againſt our Adverſaries, to this ſenſe:</p>
               <p>That muſt needs bee the true Church, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Sainct <hi>Iohns</hi> propheſie, hath had her flight to the Wilderneſſe: But ſo it is, ſuch onlie is ours, and not theirs, according to their owne confeſſion and conceſſion, whereas they ſtand to the conſtant viſibilitie thereof. Ergo, with vs ſtill is the true Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:9280:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Thus, who ſeeth not, except a borne-blinde, that our Adverſaries wrong their cauſe mightilie, through impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie, or impudencie; whereas they contende, That their Church was not onlie viſible, but ſtill actuallie ſeene? for, <hi>differunt haec duo, quantum actus &amp; potentia, adeoque non ſtatim de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinit eſſe viſibile, quod non actu videtur;</hi> it ceaſeth not ſtraight to bee viſible, which is not actuallie ſeene: which our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries ſtill confound in this argument; as who deny ſtraight the viſibilitie of a Church, except ſhee may bee ſtill actuallie pointed at by the finger: as if the Sunne cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bee viſible, whiles the ſight thereof is intercepted from vs, by the interjection of a Cloude; or through the weakneſſe of our ſeeing facultie, vnſeene of vs.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee, how variable a Church is, and may bee, us to her outward policie; ſo that our Adverſaries haue heere no juſt matter offered them of offence, whereas tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing heerein the Fathers, in whoſe words elſe they ſweare, yea, their fayth reſolveth, wee liken the Church to the Moone, <hi>propter varios, labores, defectus, eclipſes, deliquia.</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto Sainct AUGUSTINE, <hi>Ipſa est quae aliquando obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur, &amp; tanquam obnubilatur multitudine ſcandalorum; aliquando tranquillitate temporis quieta &amp; libera apparet: aliquando tribulatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; tentationum fluctibus operitur atque turbatur.</hi> But let vs heare the Church of her ſelfe, and for her ſelfe, <hi>Micab, Chap.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Rejoyce not against mee, O mine Enemie; though I fall, I ſhall aryſe: when I ſhall ſit in darkneſſe, the</hi> LORD <hi>ſhall bee a light vnto mee, &amp;c.</hi> Heere this is ſpoken in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Church, which calleth the malignant Church her enemie. Now <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> praeſupponeth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or, <hi>Est</hi> of the third adjacent, <hi>Est</hi> of the ſecond. Then the true Church may fall, and ſit in darkneſſe. Hitherto reade we, <hi>Iſaiah, Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8, where the Daughter of <hi>Zion</hi> is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a Cottage in a Vine-yarde, to a Lodge in a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Cucumbers, and to a beſiedged Citie, &amp;c. which if committed with theſe other places importing, at leaſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9280:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>poynting at her conſpicuitie and viſibilitie, ſerue to ſhew foorth her variableneſſe, and ſhadowing by turning.</p>
               <p>I know, that our Adverſaries except againſt the former part of my Diſcourſe; where I concluded from the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Church to the Chriſtian, becauſe of the great oddes heere, and diverſe priviledges of the Chriſtian Church aboue the <hi>Iewiſh:</hi> wherefore, it ſtandeth vs vpon, to eye a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe alleadged Priviledges, as wee would haue my prior Diſcourſe to remayne in its full vigour.</p>
               <p>The Priviledges of the Chriſtian Church aboue the <hi>Iewiſh,</hi> at leaſt alleadged vnto in this Argument, I finde in ſpeciall to bee theſe two: The firſt, The vniverſalitie of the one, aboue the other; and this to this ſenſe, As that there is no ſalvation without the Chriſtian, but was not ſo of the <hi>Iewiſh.</hi> The ſeconde is, That the Chriſtian hath farre fayrer and larger promiſes made to her.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt, taken from the vniverſalitie of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, leſt they might ſeeme heere to ſtand but to a bare and naked Aſſertion, they thus inſtance the matter, from <hi>Iob,</hi> and ſome yet from <hi>Melchiſedecke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That I may proceede heere the more orderlie, firſt I will treate a little in the generall of the whole matter, and then come to the particulare exceptions, and their proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>To the generall then, I would firſt inquire and learne of our Adverſaries, Whether the Church vnder the Law, and vnder Grace, bee two different Churches, or but one and the ſame in matter and ſubſtance, though differing in reſpect of the externall ſcheme or Veſture, <hi>Iewiſh</hi> or Chriſtian; as ſtill the grace diſpenſed vnder both the Covenantes, was but one and the ſame, the manner of diſpenſation but varying.</p>
               <p>Next, I would vnderſtand, Whether or not, <hi>Eadem fit analogia partium ſimilarium;</hi> ſo that what behappeneth anie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9280:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>one part, may befall another: and ſo all in common are lyable to the ſame dangers? Laſt, the Apoſtle vvideth this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe heere to our advantage, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. where hee ſhoweth, That the Chriſtian Church of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> is capable of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, incaſe ſhee perſevere not; as was the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue: nay, hee reaſoneth from rhe more to the leſſe.</p>
               <p>Now, to the particular exceptions: As to the firſt, I avouch, That the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Church ceedeth not the leaſt heere to the Chriſtian; and, That without her, there was no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. For proofe heereof, beſides diverſe other paſſages making heerevnto, let vs adviſe the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ. Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11.12; where wee ſhall ſee what is his conſtruction of the vncircumciſion, during that their ſtate: to wit, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple without CHRIST, aliants from the Common-wealth of ISRAELL, ſtrangers from the Covenants of Promiſe; yea, without hope, and without GOD in the worlde. From hence thus I reaſon:</p>
               <p>If there was anie ſalvation for thoſe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion, or for thoſe without the <hi>Iewiſhe</hi> Church, (for Circumciſion was their Sacrament of Initiation) then was there ſalvation for people without <hi>CHRIST,</hi> for aliantes from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of ISRAELL, for ſtrangers from the Covenants of Promiſe, yea, for people with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope, and without GOD in the world.</p>
               <p>But I hope our Adverſaries dare not averre that there was, or could bee, anie ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for ſuch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> There was no Salvation, or yet could bee, without the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>As to the inſtances, from which they goe about to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance this exception in the particular, of <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedecke;</hi> firſt of the firſt: I grant indeede, that it were well
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9280:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>hard divining about the tyme, or of the tyme, wherein <hi>Iob</hi> lived: but even from off of this vncertaintie I collect, That this inſtance drawne from his perſon, cannot prooue of great force, and demonſtratiuelie conclude this their point. Next, giving hee lived vnder the Law, and yet was not circumciſed, were it ſafe argumenting thus to reaſon from one particular exemple, againſt the conſtant tenour of the whole Scriptures, denying ſalvation to thoſe who were not inrolled amongſt the people of GOD by Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? Yet, if it ſhould not offende, I would gather for my ſelfe, that hee was ſo farre from living in the dayes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that at the leaſt hee lived before <hi>Abraham,</hi> out of the laſt of his Booke, at the vp-ſhot, from that his age, where it is ſayde, <hi>And after this lived</hi> IOB <hi>an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and fourtie yeares, and ſaw his ſonnes, and his ſonnes ſonnes, even foure generations, &amp;c.</hi> Now, what convenient tyme can wee aſſigne to him before this? If we aſſigne to him but ſome fiftie or ſixtie yeares, his whole dayes ſhall amount to ſome two hundreth yeares, or there-about. Now wee ſee not anie in the dayes of MOSES to haue come neare this age; nay, wee reade not of anie after ABRAHAM that came to ſuch: yea, hee lived not ſo long himſelfe. Laſt, the whole narratiue of his hiſtorie would ſeeme to make him more ancient than MOSES. But I take not vpon mee to define ought heere; onelie I would ſhowe, that our Adverſaries can argument but well weakelie, from ſo ſlender and ſo vncertaine a warrand.</p>
               <p>As to the other inſtance of MELCHISEDECK, I am aſhamed ſo much as to mention it but the leaſt: for hee is ſayd expreſlie To haue bleſſed ABRAHAM before his Circumciſion, or receiving of the ſeale of the aliance or Covenant, and To haue teethed LEVI in ABRAHAMS loynes. Truelie, <hi>magnum hic</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>hiatus multus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt MELCHISEDECK and MOSES; wherefore, this inſtance is altogether <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or impertinent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:9280:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Our Adverſaries beeing now thus deboutted from their firſt Exception, let vs ſee into the ſeconde, if it bee of anie greater force, which concerneth the Priviledge of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
               <p>I would learne of our Adverſaries, If the LORD tendered leſſe that His Church vnder the Law, than Hee doeth this vnder Grace? and, If the Promiſes were not ſemblablie made to her, as to the Chriſtian Church, by GOD, of His gracious aſſiſtance and praeſence? <hi>Hîc hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret iis aqua,</hi> the Apoſtle beeing ſo expreſſe: For amongſt the manie Priviledges of the IEW aboue the GENTILE, <hi>Rom. Cap.</hi> 9. hee reckoneth this as one, That vnto them the Promiſes were made. Nay, the Apoſtle Sainct PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER, in the ſeconde Chapter of the Actes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, at the thirtie and ninth Verſe, witneſſeth diſertlie, That the Promiſes firſt and eſpeciallie concerned the IEWES, and the GENTILES but in the next rowme: <hi>For the Promiſe is made vnto you, and to your Children, and vnto all that are afarre off, even as manie as the LORD our GOD ſhall call,</hi> &amp;c. Did not one and the ſelfe ſame Spirit, ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this one and the ſame myſticall bodie?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:9280:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Quintum Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat wee may the more happilie verſe in this buſineſſe, and travell in this matter, we would heere headilie diſtinguiſh betwixt the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall and integrant partes of a Church: for a Church may remaine and conſiſt, whiles conſtant <hi>ei ſua eſſentialia,</hi> though lamed or maimed in reſpect of her partes integrant; (I know the integrant partes to receiue their ſubdiviſion heere, into thoſe which are more or leſſe principall, or into the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and ſecundarie partes) as it is with a naturall or yet artificiall bodie: ſo that it followeth not ſtraight, That a Church ceaſeth to bee there, where ſhee is not viſible; but onlie this, That ſhee is not <hi>quoad ſua integrantia:</hi> ſo that ſhee ceaſeth onlie to bee in a certaine regarde, remaining alwayes ſimplie a Church, <hi>quantisper conſtant ei ſua eſſentialia, ſuperſunt duo aut tres Patrem in CHRISTO per Spiritum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocantes,</hi> there remaine <hi>vocatio activa &amp; paſsiva,</hi> which are the eſſentials of a Church.</p>
               <p>It reſteth then, that the want of externall policie, or outward viſibilitie, praevaileth not ſo farre, as to aboliſh ſimplie a Church. But yet as to this, wee deny not, but that it ought to bee <hi>de jure:</hi> But the quaeſtion is <hi>de facto;</hi> and of the force of this actuall want, if it bee ſuch, as prooveth deſtructive of the ſubject ſimplie, and not in a certaine regard onlie, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:9280:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Sextum Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to the promiſes made by CHRIST to his Church throughout the Goſpel, they would bee vnderſtood aright; which are indeede heere miſvnderſtood, and miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by our Adverſaries: for they draw ſtraight whatſoever promiſe is made to the whole bodie of the Church in common, to the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; nay, and require the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and fulfillment of the ſame, in everie particular Church, or in everie part of the whole. Now, from hence it is cleare, that this conſequence is verie inconſequent, that the Church ceaſeth ſimplie to bee viſible, becauſe this or that particular Church, or yet both, are devoyde of this viſibilitie: for firſt, the Church may bee viſible elſewhere: and next, the Church may remaine even there where ſhee is eclipſed of her viſibilitie, to wit, as to her eſſentials.</p>
               <p>Againe, our Adverſaries yet deceiue heere, whilſt they tye theſe promiſes of CHRIST, as <hi>De firmitate Petrae, De continua ſpiritus ſui aſsistentia,</hi> and others of the ſame note, to the externall forme of the Church; and ſo will haue them onelie to concerne that externall Policie: for ſo CHRIST ſhould ceaſe to bee the Head of His Church,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9280:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>and to His Church; whereas the Woman ſubduceth her ſelfe, and taketh her flight to the Wilderneſſe, and lurketh there. Thus that Houſe-holder, <hi>Matth. Chap.</hi> 21. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 33.34. ſhould haue caſten off all care of his Vine-yarde, whiles hee letteth it foorth to thoſe wicked and perfidious Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-men. Nay, did not CHRIST well often ſubduce Himfelfe? Did hee not take Him to flight, even praeſentlie and immediatlie after His birth and nativitie? Fled Hee not into AEGYPT, and abode there till the death of HE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ROD? and yet the Father hath appointed Him over all things, to be the head to the Church, <hi>Epheſ. Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 22.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie, our Adverſaries <hi>fraudem hic faciunt,</hi> yea, <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum manifestiſsimum,</hi> whereas they reaſon ſo in this matter, as if the holie Spirite wrought ſo in this myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, <hi>ad modum agentis naturalis, non voluntarii,</hi> as a naturall agent, and not voluntarie: for if this were the manner of the Spirites operation in the government of this myſticall bodie, then there could bee no place left for ſinne in the will, more than for errour in the mynde; there ſhould bee no place left whether for vertue or vice, for <hi>merites,</hi> or <hi>deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites;</hi> there ſhould bee no further two principles in man; hee ſhould no farther carrie about a double man, the olde and the new man: for nature worketh ſtill after one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant tenour, <hi>actiones naturales ſunt uniformes;</hi> they admit no relaxation, no intenſion or remiſſion. The Spirite then worketh in this myſticall bodie, as a voluntarie agent, and ſo admeaſureth foorth according to his owne pleaſure, <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum oeconomiam conſilii ſui non nostri arbitrii;</hi> as lykewyſe, <hi>ad modum receptivitatis ſubjecti,</hi> as wee learne to ſpeake. And laſt, GOD even ſo worketh in the workes of Grace, <hi>ut cauſas ſecundas etiam proprios ſuos motus exerere &amp; exercere ſinat,</hi> as Sainct <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayeth well, <hi>de Civitate DEI, Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Cap.</hi> 30. From whence it is, that the action <hi>ſapit ac rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let proximum canalem, tubulum, ſiphunculum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Adverſaries reaſon ſo heere, as if the Spirit not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9280:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>onlie wrought as a naturall agent, but as if hee ſhould to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and at once, <hi>agere &amp; peragere,</hi> worke and perſite this worke, which were fooliſh to vrge in nature; as if Trees ſhould come at the firſt to their perfection, as if men behoved to bee perfect at their firſt birth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Truelie the Spirit of GOD is ſtill a-working; <hi>agit quidem continuò, ſed non ſimul peragit &amp; perficit omnia, ſemper hîc locus aedificationi;</hi> then ſhall the Church bee ſtayed before her immortall Husband perfect, <hi>Vbi celebrabuntar nuptiae Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, ubi deducetur in domum mariti;</hi> till then her face ſhall not want its wrinkles, nor ſhall all teares bee wiped from her eyes.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, thoſe promiſes made by GOD to his Church, whilſt conſidered in relation to vs, are not to bee conceived as abſolute, but conditionall, <hi>ſcilicet, Si manſeritic in ſermone meo; Si ſervaveritis mandata meae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Adverſaries heere quite miſtake this point, while as they gather, that GOD cannot but continuallic aſſiſt this or that particulare Church, becauſe of that promiſe made in generall to the whole bodie in common, <hi>Ego ſum vobiſcum, &amp;c. Matthew</hi> the laſt. Howſoever ſhee car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie her ſelfe, ſhee hearken and followe the voyce of the Brydgroome, or not, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:9280:18"/>
               <head>Septimum Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas Sainct PAUL anſwering for himſelfe, <hi>Acts,</hi> 24. to that accuſation of TERTULLUS the Oratour layde foorth againſt him <hi>ad longum,</hi> allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to this, That hee worſhipped the God of his Fathers, after that way which they called Hereſie; which hee could not meane of his immediate ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Fathers, but of his mediate Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yea, of ABRAHAM, ISAAC, and IAAKOB: there is no matter, Wherefore our Adverſaries ſhould here conſtrue ſo hardlie of this, as a ſillie effuge on our part, if wee ſhould bee pleaſed to vſe this anſwere amongſt others, peradventure more preſſing, That wee worſhip the God of our Fathers, after that way which our new Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees call Hereſie, meaning by our Fathers heere, CHRIST and His Apoſtles. What letteth heere, why wee may not by way of Analogie thus repart to the quaeſtion, Of our Church her beeing before LVTHER, or, Of the beeing of our Religion, ſince the diſtance is farre leſſe heere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt vs and them, than was that Chaſme or Gulfe of two thouſand yeares betwixt ABRAHAM and PAUL?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:9280:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>Octavum Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Church ceaſeth not to bee viſible, (though not ſtill obvious, and expoſed to their ſight, who either haue not eyes to ſee, or elſe <hi>animum tantum ad infeſtandum, odii ſcilicet glau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comate excaecati,</hi> haue but a mynde to infeſt her: nay, albceit ſhee eſcape even the ſight of the ſharper ſighted,) more than that there ceaſed to bee a Church in ISRAEL in the dayes of ELIAH, whereas hee complained, that hee was left alone, and ſo could not ſee into that great number which the LORD had reſerved to himſelfe, and preſerved from bowing of the knee to BAAL: So to ſpeake heere <hi>accommodatè ad ſubjectum,</hi> albeeit that that ANTICHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIAN ſmoake before LVTHER over-whelmed ſo the Temple for a ſpace, that it could not bee diſcerned, and pointed at by the finger; it followeth not from hence, that either there was no Temple, or yet that there were no witneſſes therein, though it ſeemed ſo generallie and commonlie, albeit perhaps not vniverſallie, ſhut altogether, becauſe of that thicke miſt of ſuperſtition hanging over it, and overclouding it. Hitherto you ſee, <hi>Revel. Chap.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. how Sainct JOHN ſubjoyneth ſtraight his viſion of the open Temple, to thoſe his other viſions of AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICHRISTS tyrannie. So it reſteth, that the LORD
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9280:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>had ſtill an open Temple notwithſtanding of whatſoever ANTICHRISTS Tyrannie and Power; albeit this Temple <hi>latebat canes illos venaticos,</hi> and was not obvious, and expoſite to theſe Inquiſitours. CHRIST ceaſeth not to bee that true Light, <hi>licet tenebrae non compraehendant hanc lucem,</hi> though darkeneſſe comprehend it not, &amp;c. <hi>Lucerna lucet ſed iis qui ſunt in domo.</hi> It is not ſimplie neceſſarie, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes it diffuſe its light to thoſe that are without: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as CHRISTS Diſciples ſhut themſelues vp for feare of the people; <hi>noti erant &amp; viſi ſibi invicem,</hi> they were knowne and ſeene one to another: though they eſcaped there the ſight of thoſe, who onelie had mynds to perſecute them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Nonum Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Vt if it pleaſe you, let vs retort the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heere, and demand our Adverſaries, Where is your Church in SCOTLAND ENGLAND and the LOW-COUN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TREYS? I hope the Catholiciſme of their Church may not ſuffer them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, That they haue one heere. Now, if they affirme, That they haue one heere, let vs regeſt, <hi>atqui nullum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum vexillum,</hi> they haue no publicke, open, or avowed Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie heere, no viſible face of a Church. Then, as they muſt needs grant, That their Church lurketh heere, why
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9280:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>will they not ſuffer vs, vſing the ſame libertie, to ſay, That our Church ceaſed not to bee ſimplie, even whereas ſhee lurked, <hi>patrum nostrorum memoria,</hi> vnder Antichriſts perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, more than theirs ceaſeth to bee with vs to day?</p>
               <p>For cloſure, It would bee headilie heere adverted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, howe our adverſaries heere reaſon and conclude <hi>ab au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate, negativè, Vestra Eccleſia non fuit viſibilis, ergo non fuit;</hi> which argutation, rather than argumentation, <hi>non recto ſtat talo, aut ingreditur pede;</hi> as which deceiveth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Decimum Meletema.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the current of the ordinarie Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is intercepted, or interrupted through the iniquitie of tyme, <hi>licet hic DEO aliquid extra ordinem,</hi> the LORD may heere ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarilie ſtirre vp men to the redinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration of this broken-off worke, as the ſtorie of the olde Church, both vnder the <hi>Iudges</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> may inſtruct to the full. I would inquire of our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, <hi>Vbi interruptus fuit ille ſyndelechiſmus (notius eſt hîc illud inſtitutum</hi> DAVIDIS, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 24. <hi>quàm ut neceſſum habeam illud commemorare?</hi>) whereas the daylie Sacrifice was broken off, from whence was the redintegration or reformation heereof to bee expected? If from GOD heere <hi>extra or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem,</hi> by ſtirring vp men for his owne worke; or <hi>if ab ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9280:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>deformatoribus?</hi> and if even thoſe <hi>praebuerunt ſeſe inſtaurandae religionis adminiſtros,</hi> and ſo reparation was made even by thoſe, who in common had miſcarried (which caſe who dare ſuſtaine to denye to haue behappened?) whether or not GODS Hande is to bee acknowledged heere ſingularlie? Thus there were no danger heere, if wee ſhould bee pleaſed to recourſe to this helpe of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie vocation: for the LORD hath one and the ſame right ſtill, and may alwayes diſpoſe of his Church as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him beſt, vnder Grace, as vnder, or yet before the Law. But this were but <hi>frustra,</hi> or in vaine on our parte, <hi>ubi nulla cogit neceſsitas, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XI. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Calling even of thoſe our men, vvhich our Adverſaries ſingularlie aime at, at leaſt produce exemplar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, as of <hi>LVTHER,</hi> was ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>quoad ortum,</hi> as to his ſeparation to the worke, or to the Goſpell; though extraordinarie in ſome regard, as of thoſe heroicall motions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee was ſtirred vp, matters ſo ſtanding, to attempt a Reformation. So here we may diſtinguiſh betwixt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>reſpectu</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, his Calling was ordinarie; but <hi>reſpectu</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:9280:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it was extraordinarie; not ſo much in reſpect of the Calling in it ſelfe, but <hi>relatè ad ſubjectum,</hi> in relation to the perſon called: for as the Apoſtle Sainct <hi>Paul</hi> ſayeth, 1. <hi>Cor. Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>Quis te diſcernit?</hi> ſo to trace our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſariee heere, who ſeparated <hi>LVTHER?</hi> Truelie, <hi>ubi corpus in commune laboraret,</hi> whereas the bodie was affected in common, this his ſeparation, not to the worke ſimplie, wherevnto hee had an ordinarie calling; but in a certaine reſpect, to wit, in regarde of a greater meaſure of puritie in the worke, was, and may bee called extraordinarie.</p>
               <p>I ſay of <hi>LVTHER,</hi> That hee had an ordinarie Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the worke it ſelfe, if ſo bee that there was anie ordinarie vocation with our Adverſaries for the time: for doe they not acknowledge this, whilſt they arceſſe vs of ſeceſſion; which praeſupponeth and ſubinferreth a prior vnion, and being amongſt them? except, as it prooveth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede well ordinarie with them, they holde <hi>quod vnum rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum poſsit eſſe abſque altero; quod ſublato fundamento, locus queat eſſe termino,</hi> as yee may ſee, In that matter of their Vtopicke Purgatorie, In the retention of the puniſhment, the fault beeing remitted and pardoned; as if there could bee poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie anie place <hi>condemnationi &amp; morti,</hi> or <hi>judicio, ubi reatus nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, condemnamentum nullum,</hi> which the Apoſtle maketh as conſequents, and after-effects. Nay, which is yet farther, though wee ſhould ſimplie grant of the calling of our firſt men, that it were extraordinarie <hi>quoad ortum;</hi> the function ſhould not ceaſe from hence to bee ordinarie: for <hi>ortus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarius</hi> may giue beginning <hi>functioni ordinariae;</hi> as may bee inſtanced in <hi>Aarons</hi> Prieſthood, which was an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie function, though as to the ſpring, extraordinarie: for as to <hi>Moſes</hi> parte, it was no creation, but renunciation; hee created not, or made him Prieſt, but ſimplie renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him for Prieſt, and declared him to bee ſuch.</p>
               <p>And laſt, whereas our Adverſaries require fayth to bee made to the extraordinarie vocation of our firſt men, by
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9280:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſome miracle, or extraordinarie ſigne; truelie if wee eye the matter aright, <hi>nec hoc defuit,</hi> neither was this wanting: for I pray you whilſt they confeſſe and acknowledge, that ſo few in number, ſo obſcure in qualitie, bore out this worke ſo mightilie againſt ſo great oppoſition, doe they not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudentlie thus acknowledge GODS hand warranding this his owne calling heere miraculouſlie? for <hi>quis hic tam</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>cujus ſenſus hoc non feriat, afficiat?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XII. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ò <hi>ordinarium</hi> is to bee conſidered two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wayes: firſt, for that which is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to that order at the firſt eſtabliſhed by GOD himſelfe: and ſecondlie, for that which through an inveterated cuſtome hath commonlie obtained. Now, as to that vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation obtaining with vs to day, it is ordinarie, as to the firſt acception of the word ORDINARIE, and may indeede bee called againe extraordinarie in ſome regarde, the word being taken in the latter acception: as theirs is lykewyſe in part ordinarie, and in part extraordinarie; I ſay in part: for you would remember, that even in that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:9280:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ordination, <hi>traditur ordinato codex Evangelii, vocatur ad prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicandum Evangelium, non ſimpliciter ad ſacrificandum CHRIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVM.</hi> Wherefore, as our Adverſaries heere checke vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe words of Sainct PAUL, <hi>Nos talem conſuetudinem non habemus:</hi> ſo if the Apoſtles <hi>Patres Patrum</hi> were aliue, they ſhould not faile to except them by, the like checke, <hi>in eadem verba, Nos talem conſuetudinem non habuimus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XIII. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE haue not made the leaſt ſeceſſion from the Church of ROME, neither as ſhee is a Church, nor yet as ſuch, to wit, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered at ROME: for as to this laſt, there is no evill in the word ROMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NA; for <hi>fides Romanorum praedicata fuit per univerſum orbem:</hi> and would to GOD wee had that ancient ROME, whiles ſhee kept the Trueth in ſinceritie; but onelie from her as ſhee is <hi>Papana,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that wee may <hi>ſecerne</hi> heere <hi>ſecernenda, à Papatu,</hi> from this accident, and not from the ſubject; which is but a betaking of vs from a foule place to a cleaner, and not an egreſſion out of the Church ſimplie, (which phraſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9280:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>cannot bee vſed properlie, except ROME, which is but a ſiſter-Church, and collaterall, were the ſole Mother-Church) or a ſeceſſion from the ſame; for a ſeceſſion ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inferreth, nay, praerequireth, and praeſupponeth a prior vnion. Now <hi>Papatus</hi> and <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> Poprie and the Church make vp but one, as a ſubject doth with its common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, as <hi>Hydrops</hi> and <hi>homo</hi> doe. So the ſeceſſion of our firſt men from <hi>Poprie</hi> within the Church, was not proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie or ſimplie a ſeceſſion; but this their foorth-comming, whiles the bodie was in common affected, was rather ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatiue of a prior ſeceſſion or common defection.</p>
               <p>From hence, it might ſeeme but needleſſe, (if I might ſpeake it with reverence of greater and better judgements,) to ſeeke ſo carefullie to the juſt cauſes of our ſeceſſion, to wit, the Hereſie, Idolatrie, and Tyrannie of the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, or in the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, whereas the ground it ſelfe, or the ſeceſſion, is juſtlie denyable. Now, <hi>non entis nulla ſunt accidentia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:9280:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>XIIII. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas our Adverſaries ſuffer not that to bee called Rebaptization, whilſt they ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adde <hi>de ſuo,</hi> their toyiſh aſſumentes to that Baptiſme conferred by our men: as hereby acknowledging the Baptiſme in it ſelfe to be valide and lawfull, <hi>quòd viz. ſimus in miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, ſi non ministri,</hi> as the matter and quaeſtion was cleared and decided about BARBARIUS PHILIPPUS his acts of Praetorſhip, that they were to bee holden <hi>rata &amp; grata,</hi> and not to bee reſcinded, <hi>quòd fuerit in praetura, licet non praetor;</hi> nay, and as the caſe I hope holdeth <hi>de Ioanna Papista,</hi> who was in <hi>Papatu,</hi> though not <hi>Papa:</hi> and ſembla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie, whilſt it falleth out, that an Hereticke, nay, a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, or Necromancier poſſeſſeth the Chaire, which caſes haue proven poſſible, as the Councels can beare vs heere record.</p>
               <p>Now, that I may reaſon hence by way of Analogie, vſing the lyke libertie; Why may they not ſuffer the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and ordination obtaining with vs, goe for current, <hi>Cum noſtri ordinatores fuerint ſaltem in miniſterio, ſi non miniſtri?</hi> Or, I pray you, is Ordination of greater weight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance than Baptiſme? Or, may Baptiſme bee conferred
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:9280:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>and adminiſtred by anie not inſtructed with commiſſion? May theſe but ſuffer the leaſt divorce, which CHRIST Himſelfe hath thus coupled, MATTHEW the laſt, <hi>Ite, Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>te, Baptizate?</hi> Certes, mee thinkes it ſtrange, how our Adverſaries ſo farre foorth miſcarrie heere, as to permit to Laickes the adminiſtration of this bleſſed Sacrament; yea, farther, acknowledge it lawfull, whilſt conferred but in ſporte and merriment, and that not in the ordinarie ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, appointed by CHRIST, but in ſand, yea, and but by Children. Truelie, <hi>horret animus,</hi> yea, <hi>tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munt artus,</hi> whilſt I but ſhew <hi>quàm impiè hîc ludant in re tam ſeria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To make collection to the errande in hande, If our men may baptize, Or, if the Baptiſme conferred by them bee valide and effectuall, then they may teach, &amp; haue the warrand of <hi>Ite,</hi> are inſtructed with commiſſion; and ſo from the firſt to the laſt, <hi>viget inter nostros vocatio, vel ipſis hic Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſariis nobis ſuffragantibus astipulantibus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:9280:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>XV. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N that Vocation or Calling obtayning with our Adverſaries, and which our men brought from thence with them, (giving wee had our Calling of them) theſe three acts are diſtinctlie to bee conſidered; GODS owne act, <hi>penes quem ſummum vocandi jus, ac mittendi imperium,</hi> and from whome is that inward Calling; next, The Church her act, from which as GODS Inſtrument in this worke is that externall, or outward Calling; The third is of the Church popiſhlie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, or of the Pope his act, and of his Bond-ſlaues, from whence is <hi>vitium Vocationis,</hi> or that faultineſſe and vitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie in the Calling. Nowe, this laſt cannot <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or make devoyde, and of null effect and force the two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; ſo that there remayneth ſtill a Calling amongſt our Adverſaries, though well vitious. Thus whereas our men came as it were foorth from amongſt them, they but renounced this latter parte, conſtantlie retayning <hi>quod DEI erat, &amp; quod Eccleſiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is to bee adverted heere, That wee traduce not even thoſe Ordinations obtayning to daye with our Adverſaries <hi>pro nullis, ſed pro vitioſis;</hi> as wee acknowledge a Church
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9280:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>with them, whiles the matrimoniall Tables are not rent, or repeated, nor a Bill of divorce given, <hi>ubi libellus repudii?</hi> as it fared with the adulterous ISRAELITES, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued GODS people even after their manie adulteries and ſpirituall whoredomes: I ſay, that wee acknowledge their Church as <hi>veram Eccleſiam,</hi> though not <hi>veracem,</hi> as a true Church, in regard of a Phyſicall veritie, though not of an Ethicall veracitie.</p>
               <p>Alwayes, it is to bee conſidered headilie, howe the caſe heere altereth, whilſt their ordinations are not ſo much as warrandable by their owne Canons, as whereas they deferred orders to Idiots and Children: for heere <hi>non habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus hujuſinodi ordinationes pro vitioſis, ſed pro nullis:</hi> for the lawfulneſſe of the Cheirotheſie dependeth from the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the praeceeding Cheirotonie, and not on the contrarie, this from that other; the ſigne beeing ſuſpended from the matter, and not the matter from the ſigne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9280:24"/>
               <head>XVI. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here-as there concurre and occurre ſome three actes even in that Voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion obtayning with our Adverſaries, and ſo in that Calling which our firſt men brought from thence; ſo the concurrence and occurrence of the ſame are neceſſarie to a lawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: for the ſame muſt occurre and concurre to a lawfull deſtitution, which to the prior inſtitution. For exemple, Where King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes come by election, the ſame conſentes are required to a Kings deſtitutione, which to his prior inſtitution in <hi>Regem;</hi> and elſe, to meddle with the ſacred perſon of a King, is to touch and meddle with the LORDS anoynted: yea, and to faile and fault even againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Theſe are hitherto; to meete heere with our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, excepting, that wee haue loſed by excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, what right wee had from amongſt them formerlie by anie vocation. Certes, the Pope heere cannot <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or make of no force, neither <hi>quod DEI est,</hi> nor yet <hi>quod Eccleſiae.</hi> Nay, in common, and promiſcuous marriages, <hi>multa quae impediunt contrahendum, non dirimunt contractum.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, without the concurrence and occurrence of the whole actes in the deſtitution, which occurred and concurred to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9280:25"/>the prior inſtitution, the proceedure is well ſummarie and vnformall, as I hope is cleare from the inſtanced exemple. I leaue to ſpeake of the ground of the excommunication, according wherevnto judgement muſt bee given of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication it ſelfe; where it feareth mee, the matter hath proceeded <hi>clave errante.</hi> As lykewyſe, <hi>quod non ſtatim rumpatur interius illud ſpiritus coagulum, vbi rumpitur exterius il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud vinculum;</hi> giving that a ſiſter-Church, to wit, the <hi>Romane</hi> Church, could haue lawfullie ſentenced vs, where-about <hi>ſub judice lis est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>XVII. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas out of the common Colledge of Presbyters, or Elders, one began to bee praefected over the reſt, and bee ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſo called by the name of BISHOP, (I diſpute not heere, whether this Bee <hi>ju ris divini,</hi> or <hi>poſitivi</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the act of Ordination, or matter it ſelfe remained common, <hi>ſolâ</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>ritu ordinandi manente penes Epiſcopum ſingulariter,</hi> the ſole Rite or externall ſigne of ordination being appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to the BISHOP ſingularlie.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:9280:25"/>But no, not even then, whereas this cuſtome firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and was in its greateſt vigour, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, was the Rite or the externall ſigne <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſcilicet, ſolelie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Biſhops ſo called in oppoſition, as that it was not adminiſtred and peracted by Presbyters; as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heere, Sainct AMBROSE and AUGUSTINE, beare vs recorde; and ALEXANDRIA and AEGYPT can beare witneſſe, where <hi>conſignabant,</hi> or <hi>conſecrabant &amp; Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteri:</hi> for the one vſeth the word <hi>Conſignandi,</hi> as the other <hi>Conſecrandi.</hi> Nay, ſeeing it cannot bee denyed, <hi>actum ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi, rem ipſam,</hi> ſcilicet, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is the greater part, <hi>manſiſſe penes &amp; Preſbyteros,</hi> what letteth why that which is but the leſſer part, the ſigne or the bare and naked Rite, may not remaine common to Presbyters with Biſhops ſo called antitheticallie? for <hi>cui competit quod majus eſt eidem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribi nil vetat quod minus eſt, modo ſint ejuſdem generis:</hi> but the gendre is ſtill kept, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It ſtandeth vs vpon yet a little to eye more nearlie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this matter, becauſe of our Adverſaries. Sainct CHRY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SOSTOME, poſing the quaeſtion <hi>cur Apost. ad Philip. tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eat ab Epiſcopat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ad Diaconatum, nullo relicto loco intermedio</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Preſbyterorum,</hi> thus anſwereth the matter, <hi>Quod</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that the order is but one and the ſame: and ſtraight ſubjoyneth, <hi>quòd eadem conveniant Preſbyteris, quae Epiſcopis,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſayech hee, to the one which to the other: nay, which is yet farther, hee ſpeaketh more peremptorilie to the matter, and ſayth poſitiuelie, that the Biſhops heerein wrong the Presbyters, That they appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate this ſingularlie to themſelues, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I know this place to bee wreſted to the contrarie, to the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this their praerogatiue, as if the ſame were the force of the word heere in compoſition, which it carrieth, whilſt reſolved in its pure ſimples, whereas <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9280:26"/>
                  <hi>cum Chryſoſtomo,</hi> beareth this other ſignification, which is quite contrarie. And leſt this might ſeeme but an ydle Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, not having anie foundation in the trueth, I pray you obſerue with mee the vſe of this word in ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as I. <hi>Theſſ. Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ne quis opprimat aut circumveniat fratrem ſuum in negotio,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I forbeare heere to meddle with that idle difference, ſo hotlie and contentiouſlie toſſed and agitated amongſt vs to day, Whether a Biſhop bee greater, than a Presbyter, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione Dominica,</hi> or <hi>dispoſitione Eccleſiastica;</hi> whereas it were farre ſafer, <hi>privatas has ſimultates deponere, quò melius reipub. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianae in communi poſſemus conſulere;</hi> yea, and where <hi>fruſtra con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentioſum funem ducimus:</hi> as who may agree in the matter, without great prejudice to the trueth, ſcilicet, that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is but one and the ſame, admitting alwayes a diſpari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or difference of degree <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and this not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute or ſimple, but relatiue or reſpectiue <hi>ad</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the different meaſure of graces and gifts in the LORDS worke-men, and ſutablie to CHRISTS inſtitution, who gaue ſome to bee Apoſtles, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſo foorth. Nay, according to that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, at leaſt ſubinſinuated and implyed difference, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritie amongſt the Apoſtles, where ſome are called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, beſides ſome other names to this ſame purpoſe, importing, at leaſt bewraying a diſtinction.</p>
               <p>But to the matter againe <hi>vnde digreſsi</hi> you ſee howe Sainct HIEROME prooveth this power of Ordination to bee common to Presbyters with Biſhops, by an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken from the more to the leſſe. <hi>Quod qui poſſunt corpus CHRISTI conficere, poſsint &amp; Preſbyterum creare;</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept (forſooth) it bee more to conſigne a Presbyter, than to create our owne Creator. To this ſame ſenſe and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I would poſe our Adverſaries heere a little, <hi>poſſuntne
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9280:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Preſbyteri,</hi> ſo called antitheticallie, or in oppoſition, <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num efficere,</hi> or <hi>baptizare?</hi> I take theſe for one <hi>ex bypotheſi ad bominem;</hi> for our Adverſaries holde and maintaine, <hi>quod per Baptiſmum character indelebilis imprimatur,</hi> That by Baptiſme an indelible character is imprinted. Now, there is none who can deny, but that this latter may bee adſcrybed to anie Gregarie Presbyter; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the firſt may bee ſaide to bee no leſſe competent vnto him.</p>
               <p>As to thoſe places of the Apoſtle, where this ſeemeth ſingularlie to bee adſcrybed vnto one, they are to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>communiter,</hi> or in common to bee vnderſtood: for <hi>non ſtatim de caeteris negatur, quod de uno praedicatur;</hi> yea, heerefore what the Apoſtle ſeemed ſingularlie to haue taken and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed vnto himſelfe in the one place, 2. <hi>Timoth. Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6, hee ſhoweth plainlie ao haue bene common to the whole Elderſhip, 1. <hi>Timoth. Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>I feare to wade anie farther in this point: for <hi>non niſe caute incedendum per ignes ſuppoſitos cineri doloſo; adeoque offendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula vel in ipſis picturis nudis tollenda.</hi> And yet I neede not feare much the incurring heere the offence of anie, <hi>ut qui Epiſcoporum axioma ne vel minimum hîc eam imminutum,</hi> ſo farre foorth as I can trace anie light going before mee, for war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand and appuy to my conſcience: for as to that Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of order without power, whether abſolute or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation, which may ſuffer vpon abuſe repetition by the partie delegating, I cannot ſo much as by dreame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thereof: for albeit all bee called to one and the ſame Miniſtrie, it followeth not ſtraight, <hi>quod ſimil &amp; quiſque vocetur ad parem in ministerio gradum,</hi> more than in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Iuſtice all are of alyke power and dignitie in place: nor yet of that Orbiculare praeſidence falſelie fathered vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sainct AMBROSE, vpon a wyde miſinterpretation and miſtaking of his mynde; <hi>cum varii ſint modi recedendi,</hi> as alſo that ſo I could not ſee, howe the firſt Presbyter
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9280:27"/>could bee called by the name of Biſhop ſingularlie; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in a circle there is nothing firſt or laſt, <hi>niſi recurras ad puncta imaginaria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how-ſo-ever the matter goe, this muſt bee given to the praeſent neceſſitie, becauſe of our Adverſaries excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting heere againſt the lawfulneſſe of that by-gone Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie with vs theſe diverſe yeares heere-to-fore, <hi>quod nostri destituti fuerint</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Epiſcopali.</hi> You ſee that this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not evacuate, or but the leaſt enervate our Calling; both theſe beeing but one, the word beeing taken <hi>ex uſu Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> where wee ſee the one ſubjoyned to the other exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geticallie, as <hi>Acts, Chap.</hi> 20. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 28. The Elders of the Church of EPHESUS accerſed, or ſent for to MILE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVM, are exhorted to take heede to themſelues, and to their Flockes, over the which the holie Ghoſt <hi>praefecit cos Epiſcopos,</hi> had made them Over-ſeers. As lykewyſe, wee ſee th'Apoſtle to paſſe ſtraight fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Name to the Office, which would argue a communion in the one, as in the other: nay, wee ſee the Apoſtle to require the ſame thing in a Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, which in a Biſhop; which ſubinferreth a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie competencie of the ſame in common to both.</p>
               <p>As laſt, wee ſee the Apoſtle Sainct PETER himſelfe, <hi>&amp; ſynpreſbyterum ſeſe indigetare.</hi> But beſides this, that both theſe are but one and the ſame, the wordes beeing taken <hi>exuſu Scripturae,</hi> true is it not, that all our firſt men were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde of this ſorte of Ordination, which our Adverſaries ſo praeciſelie vrge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:9280:27"/>
               <head>XVIII. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eſt there might ſeeme heere juſtlie not the leaſt part of this worke wanting, if I ſhould over-paſſe by ſilence that point of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which our Adverſaries eſteeme to bee of ſuch poyſe and weight, as if without it there could bee no lawfull Church nor Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie; it ſtandeth vs vpon to ſpeake ſo farre foorth of it, as the praeſent neceſſitie requireth.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, ſeeing <hi>nullum apud eos ſonorius crepitaculum, quo vehementius nos obtundant,</hi> I ſhall touch it a little <hi>en paſſant,</hi> if it were but to ſilence their ſo clamorous cryes here; though it may bee, if GOD ſhall giue grace and leaue, I ſpeake more properlie and fuſelie of this argument in its proper place, Of the notes of the Church.</p>
               <p>In the entrie heere, I pray you alwayes to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that it was the doctrinall, and not perſonall ſucceſſion, which thoſe Ancientes ſo highlie regarded, and that they mentioned but this laſt, becauſe of the firſt, as which is the verie ſoule and lyfe thereof. Againe, it would bee
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9280:28"/>headilie reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred here, that thoſe Haeretiks, againſt who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe Ancients inſtituted their Diſputations, by alleadging to the perſons profeſſing, and not to the doctrine profeſſed, (as wee ſee TERTULLIANE to reaſon againſt the MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIONITES and GNOSTICKS; <hi>Edant Origines Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum ſuorum, evolvant ſeriem antiſtitum it a per ſucceſsionem ab initio decurrentem, vt primus ille Epiſcopus aliquem ex Apoſtolis vel Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicis viris habuerit auctorem &amp; anteceſſorem; hoc enim modo Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manorum Eccleſia</hi> CLEMENTEM <hi>à</hi> PETRO <hi>ordinatum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert, confingant tale aliquid haeretici,</hi> &amp;c.) that thoſe Haereticks, I ſay, denyed, eyther in whole, or in part, the Scriptures, wherethrough the Diſpute could not bee inſtituted from hence againſt ſuch. So then, thus the Ancientes adorted thoſe Haeretickes, and improoved their doctrine, becauſe they could not ſhow anie conſtant profeſſion of the ſame, they could not point at thoſe Biſhops who profeſſed with them, where the ROMANE Church is well often exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plarlie alleadged vnto. But it is to bee obſerved, howe <hi>Tertulliane</hi> in the alleadged place, alleadgeth the exemple of the Church of SMYRNA, as a Tranſmarine Church, as hee doth the exemple of the Church of ROME, as a Ciſmarine Church; that ſo hee might ſhew evidentlie, <hi>doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Novati, Marcionis novam &amp; inauditam prorſus fuiſſe,</hi> as which was not acknowledged, or believed by anie Church at all, whether on this ſide of the Sea, or beyonde the Sea. Thus then, it was to this ſenſe, that the Ancients vrged the argument from ſucceſſion; from whence it is cleare, that the perſonall ſucceſſion was ſtill alleadged vnto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the doctrinall onlie.</p>
               <p>But to ſpeake conciſelie and ſinewiſhlie of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, firſt wee ſhall ſhow, GOD willing, That there is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of this ſucceſſion, which our Adverſaries ſolelie and ſingularlie require. Next, that this ſort of ſucceſſion is not findable with themſelues. Laſt, That we haue that ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which is neceſſarie <hi>penes nos<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> or with vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:9280:28"/>That I may borrow mine empledged worde, let mee, as to the firſt, packe vp the matter by forme of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>If ſo bee, that perſonall and locall ſucceſſion ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red even then and there interruption, where it was of greater neceſſitie, it followeth, that it may ſuffer the lyke with the leſſe danger, where it is of leſſer neceſſitie:</p>
               <p>But ſo it is, the firſt holdeth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth true:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> the ſame judgement muſt bee given in this latter caſe.</p>
               <p>For probation of the minor; the Prieſthood of AA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RON may ſerue to the full, from whence wee thus binde vp the Argument.</p>
               <p>Whereas the Prieſthood vnder the Law was tyed to AARONS carnall deſcent, truelie then this perſonall ſucceſſion behooved to bee of greater ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, than it can bee now vnder Grace, where the matter goeth by free election:</p>
               <p>But ſo it is, that even then this perſonall ſucceſſion ſuffered diverſlie interruption:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> it may admit yet the lyke interruption, without the leaſt danger, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>For probation of the minor; were not NADAE and ABIHU ſtricken with fire from Heaven, who ſhould haue ſucceeded by Line? Next, whereas it came to ELEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZAR, I would enquire, if it continued ſtill in him and his race? Was it not vpon their abuſe tranſlated to the ſtocke of ITHAMAR? Now, reſted it in the ſtocke of ITHAMAR? Was it not broken off, becauſe of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:9280:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>of ELIES ſonnes, HOPHNI and PHINE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAS, albeit it had well long continued in the houſe of ELI? Was not ABIATHAR the laſt Prieſt of that ſtocke depoſed by SALOMON, and ZADOK ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and ſuffected in his vice and place? Thus I hope it may appeare moſt evidentlie, to anie who ſhutteth not his eyes wilfullie againſt this ſo cleare a light, from this my ſo long deduction of the matter, That the Church is not tyed to anie perſonall ſucceſſion, ſuite, or traine of Biſhops; which were heere indeede to lay a falſe reckoning and compt; as if <hi>filii</hi> ABRAHAE <hi>omnes ſecundum carnem cenſendi eſſent in ſemine,</hi> and not theſe onlie, who are Children after the Promiſe.</p>
               <p>In the next roome, I would haue you with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and headineſſe to advert heere, that the place gaue the praeheminence to the perſons, and not the perſons the dignitie or primacie to the Seage or Seate: That is, that it was not whether the reſidence or death of an Apoſtle, in this or that Seage or Seate, which gaue the procathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie, and praeſeance heere to the after ſucceeding Biſhops in that Seage, or in that Sea; from whence our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries collect and conclude the Procathedrie, nay, that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Proſtaſie of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> as Sainct <hi>Peters</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, forſooth, <hi>in ſedem Apostolicam:</hi> but that the Seages or Seas received this praeheminence, according to that ranke they helde and obtained as Cities of the Empyre: for elſe, I hope it could not bee well denyed, but that the firſt place heere were due to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> before <hi>Rome,</hi> if ſucceſſion can make ought to the praeheminenee or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie of place: for did not CHRIST Himſelfe preach, yea, and ſuffer at <hi>Hieruſalem?</hi> Nay, did Hee not accompliſh there all the myſteries of our Salvation? Did not all the Apoſtles iſſue as it were from thence? Preach, yea, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide there for a goodlie ſpace? Doe not the Ancients here agree as it were in common, That <hi>Iames</hi> turned the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:9280:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>Biſhop of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> whereas the matter of <hi>Peters</hi> beeing at <hi>Rome,</hi> and Biſhopricke there, is at leaſt ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>I would poſe our Adverſaries heere a little, How is it heere, that the Biſhop of <hi>HIERVSALEM</hi> was not reputed and holden for the firſt Biſhop, if the perſons gaue the primacie or praeheminence to the place? Nay, wee ſee it eſpeciallie provided, <hi>Concil. Nie.</hi> 1. <hi>Can.</hi> 6. that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſhould bee deferred to the Biſhop of <hi>HIERVSA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEM,</hi> without the leaſt praejudice to that honour and regarde due by him to the Biſhop of <hi>CAESARIA,</hi> his Metrapolitane. Thus it is cleare from hence, That this ſort of praeheminence in thoſe Apoſtolicke Seages, or Seas, was vnknowne then in thoſe olde tymes, and to thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Fathers, gathered at that Councell.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie, giving heere liberallie for the tyme, That a conſtant and vninterrupted ſucceſſion of Biſhops were an infallible note of a true Church, wherefore ſhould not this militate aſwell for the three other Seages, of <hi>ALEX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ANDRIA, ANTIOCHIA, HIERVSA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEM,</hi> as for the Sea of <hi>ROME;</hi> ſeeing, as <hi>EV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEBIVS</hi> witneſſeth in his Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtorie, <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. that they haue this ſucceſsion? Why then ſhould the Church of <hi>ROME</hi> bee more inſtyled by the name of the true, ſole, Catholicke, and Apoſtolicke Church, than the Church of <hi>ALEXANDRIA, ANTIOCH,</hi> &amp;c? What can this ſucceſsion to <hi>PETER in ſedem Romanam,</hi> import and rapport, beyond the ſuccesſion to anie Apoſtle elſe, into anie other Seage or Seat? I would bee glad to bee inſtructed heere, where I promiſe to follow the light, as <hi>docilem me praebere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthlie, If this ſorte of Succeſſion, to wit, perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and locall, which is the onelie Succeſſion vrged and requyred by our Adverſaries, were ſimplie neceſſarie to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:9280:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>the conſtitution of a true Church, and lawfull Miniſtrie, and were an infallible, if not conſtitutiue, at leaſt often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue note of a true Church; then wee behooved to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that Church ſtraight for a true Church, where this were to bee found: For <hi>nota debet</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>retrocommeat</hi> with the ſubject noted, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>riſibile</hi> doeth <hi>cum homine:</hi> but I hope our Adverſaries ſhall not ſtande heerevnto; for then they behooved to acknowledge the <hi>GREEKE</hi> Church for a true and lawfull Church, which they moſt pertinaciouſlie heere denye: for <hi>&amp; haec bâc Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsione gaudet, poſſent &amp; hi longam ſeriem texere, Catalogum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituere EPISCOPORVM.</hi> Nay, then the <hi>AR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIANS</hi> ſhould haue made vp a true Church, becauſe of this Succeſſion obtayning lykewyſe with them.</p>
               <p>Our Adverſaries heere finding themſelues ſtrayted, are driven to ſeeke to ſome poſture, whitherto they affirme, That the Argument proceedeth heere but negatiuelie; that is, That it ſerveth not ſo much to ſhowe vvhere the Church is, or, What is the true Church; as Where ſhee is not. Where-vpon it followeth, That this Succeſsion ſhall bee <hi>nota non nota,</hi> or <hi>nota non notificans,</hi> a note not no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying or poynting foorth the ſubject; which is to convell the fundaments of all true and ſound Philoſophie.</p>
               <p>But to trace them yet heere, and deject them from this refuge: Thus there ſhoulde not haue beene a Church in the beginning; neyther ſhoulde there bee one at the conſummation of the worlde: as where <hi>utrobique hic defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus comparet, haec ſucceſsio deſideratur,</hi> this Succeſsion is vvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Wherefore, the Argument proceedeth not ſo much as by way of negation.</p>
               <p>Fiftlie: The practiſe of the Primitiue Church ſtandeth heere to the contrarie: where wee finde a double ſorte of Vocation, where-of <hi>una fiebat</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>alia</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:9280:30"/>Nowe, I woulde vnderſtande of our Adverſaries, their judgement of and about thoſe Ordinations vſed by thoſe olde ancient Fathers, which were called abſolutelie; If they bee to them, or with them, eyther for null, or for vitious? But ſo it is, This Succeſsion which they preſſe, to wit, perſonall and locall, was heere wanting, where-in they place the verie eſſence of Succeſsion, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sixtlie: I would inquyre of our Adverſaries, Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>CONSTANTINOPLE</hi> vvas made a Patriarchall Seate, <hi>tempore THEODOSII Magni,</hi> which Citie before was ſtill ſubject <hi>HERACLENSI Epiſcopo; tantum abeſt ut CONSTANTINOPOLITANVS Epiſcopus fuerit Patriarcha, ut ne Metropolites quidem:</hi> Whether or not they vvill take vpon them heere to condemne this, becauſe of this defect of a perſonall and locall Succeſsion in <hi>Caput;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though elſe it was a cooptation <hi>in commune corpus, tagma, Collegium, ſyſtema reliquorum Patriarcharum,</hi> according to thoſe abſolute Ordinations vſed of olde by thoſe auncient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Seaventhlie: If this Succeſsion perſonall and locall, were ſimplie heere neceſſarie, then it ſhoulde followe to their great praejudice heere, <hi>quòd nulli novi Epiſcopatus poſſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, inſtitui,</hi> That no newe Biſhoprickes could bee erected: ſo that heere they praejudge, through imprudencie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſideration, their ſo due and juſt deſerved prayſe, of their ſo fruitfull labours amongſt the <hi>INDIANS,</hi> where they haue builded and created ſo manie newe CHUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHES, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all: Where-as our verie Adverſaries conclude this poynt from that Succeſsion of the Iudges of <hi>ISRAEL,</hi> vvhy may they not admit heere, That this Succeſsion may fuffer interruption? as wee ſee that to haue beene reapſe diverſelie, and eft-ſoones interrupted vnder their diverſe enemies, <hi>MOABITES, CANANITES, AMO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RITES,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:9280:31"/>and ſo foorth; and that nowe for longer, and nowe for ſhorter ſpace; as nowe for the ſpace of twentie yeares, nowe of ſeaven, yea, nowe of whole fourtie. Truelie, this Argument heere militateth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Thus I hope I haue improven to the verie full, the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie of this Succeſsion, to wit, perſonall and locall, vvhich our Adverſaries heere vrge and preſſe ſo much.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond I promiſed to prooue, that is, That this Succeſsion is not to bee found with our verie Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, I ſhall, GOD vvilling, prooue this by infallible demonſtrations.</p>
               <p>No Haereticke hath <hi>jus ordinandi,</hi> or power of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, even according to ſome of their owne Canons: (Thus I argue not by poſition, but of ſuppoſition onelie <hi>ad hominem:</hi> vvhere I denye not lykewyſe <hi>BABEL</hi> to bee confounded, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But ſo it is, that manie and diverſe of their Popes haue proven ſuch:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> for the leaſt during this ſpace, this Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath ſuffered interruption: nay, it followeth from hence, That there hath beene no lawfull Church, or Miniſtrie vvith them ſince, ſo much as vvarrandable by their owne Canons.</p>
               <p>For probation of the minor: Our probation ſhall not ſtay it ſelfe heere in the Scriptures, which were indeede ſufficient, but of ſurpluſſge, and for the clearer conviction of our Adverſaries, and to take from them all effuge &amp; means to eſcape heere, I offer mee to prooue, That diverſe Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes haue poſſeſſed that Chaire, and occupied the ſame, even according to that way which themſelues call Haereſie: where I may reckon foorth a great traine of them, as were <hi>LIBERIVS, FOELIX</hi> the ſecond, <hi>LEO</hi> the firſt, <hi>GELASIVS</hi> the firſt, <hi>VIGILIVS, GREGORIE</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:9280:31"/>the ſecond, <hi>ZACHARIE</hi> the firſt, <hi>ADRIAN</hi> the firſt, <hi>NICOLAS</hi> the firſt, <hi>IOHN</hi> the eight, <hi>NI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>COLAS</hi> the ſecond, <hi>COELESTINE</hi> the third, <hi>INNOCENT</hi> the third, <hi>IOHN</hi> the twentie-two, and <hi>INNOCENT</hi> the eight; all which haue erred in that which concerneth the Fayth; elſe our Moderne Doctours prooue heterodoxe, as who holde not, nor maintaine the ſame doctrine with them.</p>
               <p>But for ſhortneſſe ſake, I will content mee to poynt at thoſe who haue beene condemned for ſuch, by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Councels. Firſt then, I would poſe our Adverſaries, what they can ſay to <hi>HONORIVS</hi> the firſt, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in two generall Councels, the ſixt and the ſeaventh; and anathematized as an Haereticke, for a Monothelite?</p>
               <p>Our Seraphicke Doctor <hi>BELLARMINE</hi> can tell vs heere, that <hi>HONORIVS</hi> erred, but as a private man heere, and not as Pope. A braue eſchappatoire, forſooth, <hi>ficulneum ADAMI praeſidium,</hi> a fine Coate of figge-tree leaues, to cover his nakedneſſe. I pray you, if <hi>HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIVS</hi> beeing conſulted as Pope in a matter of Fayth, controverted vpon for the time, anſwered not to the point as Pope, but as a private Doctor or man; in what poſterne ſhall wee ſeeke his Holineſſe, forſooth, whereas his perſon ſpeaketh to vs, that wee bee no farther heere deceived? Nay truelie, if ſo bee hee may erre, whereas adviſed and conſulted in a matter of Fayth, I ſee not what profite his pretended priviledge of not erring, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, can rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port heere to the Church.</p>
               <p>But this cannot helpe our Adverſarie heere; for <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORIVS</hi> was anathematized as Biſhop of <hi>ROME,</hi> and not as a private man, or Doctor. Nay, which is yet farther, <hi>LEO</hi> the ſecond, his owne ſucceſſour, confeſſeth of <hi>HONORIVS,</hi> that hee polluted that holie Seage or Sea: wherevpon it followeth by an inevitable conſequence,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:9280:32"/>that hee erred as Pope: for elſe his private ſouilleurs, or pollutions, could not haue polluted this ſacred Seage.</p>
               <p>Laſt, for my ſelfe, I would not bee heere curious for the ſecond perſon of the Pope his Holineſſe: but would bee content to take order with his private perſon, for his miſcarriage, forbearing his Holineſſe, or the ſecond perſon hee ſuſtaineth out of pure and meere religion, for-ſooth.</p>
               <p>Next, I would learne what our Adverſaries can ſay to <hi>IOHN</hi> the twelft, condemned for moſt enormious crymes, in a Councell holden at <hi>ROME,</hi> as for carow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Wyne, for loue of the Devill, for directing his devotion, at leaſt in ſport and merriment, to <hi>IVPITER</hi> and <hi>MARS,</hi> I, to <hi>IVPITER</hi> and <hi>VENVS</hi> their Proprogoddeſſe! What will they ſaye to <hi>IOHN</hi> the three and twentieth, or foure and twentieth, denying the Reſurrection, condemned in the Councell of <hi>CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANCE?</hi> Laſt, what can they except againſt <hi>EV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GENIVS</hi> the fourth, depoſed in the Councell of <hi>BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIL,</hi> and condemned for Haereticke? Now, <hi>quicquid h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Epiſcoporum, aut ordinis <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſupereſt in Eccleſia Romana, ad hoc fonte profluxit:</hi> and ſo it followeth, that theſe two hundreth yeares ſince, or there-abouts, there hath beene no lawfull Vocation with our Adverſaries, which they can warrand by their owne Canons. Now, <hi>quis dabit mundum ex immundo,</hi> who can bring a cleane thing out of filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>It is worthie our beſt obſervation, that BELLAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINE having acknowledged, even by the force of the Trueth, That this Councell was lawfullie indicted: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon it followth, after their owne Canons, that ſo it could not erre; ſayeth, That it turned vitious: and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as hee poynteth at the faultineſſe thereof, it is heere, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, <hi>quod pronunciarit ſecundum Concilium.</hi> Truelie, it is well heere, that they may authorize, or exauthorize, at
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:9280:32"/>their pleaſure, as they finde ought to make for them, or againſt them.</p>
               <p>I ſhould but miſſ-ſpende good tyme, if I ſhould rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon foorth all thoſe vitious and monſtrous heads the haue adapted to this bodie, ſome Infidels, ſome Magitians, ſome Necromancers, as <hi>SYLVESTER</hi> the ſecond; ſome attayning to the Popedome by brigandiſe, by Armes, ſome by one fineſſe, and ſome by another; ſcarce one amongſt numbers entering in at the Doore ſo much as of an externall Vocation, warrandable by their owne Canons. Nay, I might heere arceſſe them all in common of Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: for if all came not thus by the place, at leaſt all to one thus carrie themſelues in the place: for they expoſe to ſale the Graces and Giftes of GOD, and holde them get-able by Money; as their Nundination of Indulgences, Soule-Maſſes, and their other Wares of this Note, may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct to the full; where-thorow they approoue themſelues to haue ſucceeded indeede to <hi>SIMON,</hi> but <hi>SIMON MAGVS,</hi> and not SIMON PETER, to bee his ſingular Succeſſours.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Vendit Alexander Claves, Altaria, Chriſtum.</l>
                  <l>Vendere jure potest: emerat ipſe prius.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And BAPTISTA MANTVANVS to this ſame ſenſe:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>— venalia nobis</l>
                  <l>Templa, Sacerdotes, Altaria, Sacra, Coronae,</l>
                  <l>Ignis, Thura, Preces, Coelum eſt venale, <abbr>Deuſque.</abbr>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>I would vnderſtand of our Adverſaries, If their ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was canonicall, who came thus by the Popedome, as by Simonie, Brigandiſe, Armes, &amp;c.?</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>LEO</hi> telleth vs, that thoſe foure are required to a canonicall and lawfull Election, <hi>vota civium, teſtimonia
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:9280:33"/>populorum, arbitri a honoratorum, electio cleri.</hi> Now, I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand our Adverſaries heere, If the free ſuffrages of the people bee ſo much as required to the election of a Pope to day? And yet <hi>BELLARMINE</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Lib. de Clericis, Cap.</hi> 7. is forced to confeſſe, That of olde none was holden for lawfull Biſhop, who wanted the ſuffiages of the people to his election: wherevpon it followeth, that they walke not in the olde waye, but they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyned in the latter dayes.</p>
               <p>I would faine learne of our Adverſaries, Whether this Succeſſion was free from ſuffering interruption, whereas the ROMISH Biſhops were divided amongſt themſelues by Schiſmes, for manie yeares together? I remit the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heere to that great papiſt ONUPHRIUS, <hi>in Chronico,</hi> where hee reckoneth foorth roundlie ſome thirtie Schiſmes in the Church of ROME: as the firſt, betweene COR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NELIUS and NOVATUS; the ſecond, betwixt LI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERIUS and FOELIX; the third, betwixt DAMA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS and VRCISINUS, which prooved a well bloodie Schiſme; and ſo foorth of the reſt of that note.</p>
               <p>I would in like manner inquire heere, Where one Pope diſanulled the Actes of another, and reordained thoſe who formerlie had received orders of his Deceſſour, as thus not acknowledging that prior Ordination for lawfull and valide; as, for inſtance, Pope SERGIUS the third, carried him towardes his deceſſour Pope FORMOSUS, beſides diverſe other inſtances, whether of thoſe conteſting Fathers ſhall wee acknowledge for his Holineſſe, and from whether ſhall wee deriue and aeſtimate the ſucceſſion? Truelie, <hi>dignus hic vindice nodus.</hi> I hope thoſe may ſuffice heere <hi>ad guſtum,</hi> yea, and to bring in diſtaſte this their ſo much boaſted-of Succeſſion, with thoſe whoſe ſenſorie is not altogether diſtempered; yea, who are not devoide of the ſenſe of taſting.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:9280:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>Certes, the providence of GOD is ſingularlie to bee admired heere, in that Hee hath not ſuffered thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations and Monumentes, of the turpitude of this holie Seage, for-ſooth, to bee ſo farre foorth ſuppreſſed, as that we haue not ſufficiencie of proofe for cleare conviction of the ADVERSARIE; and yet queſtionleſſe <hi>hî non defuerant ſibi,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But to arceſſe this matter from on high, and deduce it <hi>vel à capite,</hi> from <hi>PETER'S</hi> beeing at <hi>ROME;</hi> if wee ſhewe but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that <hi>PETER</hi> was never there, the after-ſubſtruction falleth of will: wherefore, thus I argue:</p>
               <p>If Sainct <hi>PETER</hi> was never at <hi>ROME,</hi> then this Succeſsion to him into that Seate or Seage ceaſeth:</p>
               <p>But ſo it is, Sainct <hi>PETER</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> this Succeſsion ceaſeth, and falleth of will.</p>
               <p>For probation of the minor, I purpoſe not no treate of this <hi>ad longum,</hi> but onelie ſo farre foorth as the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the praeſent errand requireth: ſo that I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelfe heere but to poynt at ſome few thinges, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erto vel intento demum digito.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the entrie heere, I would haue you to obſerue theſe generalles: That the firſt Father or Author of this Forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, is one <hi>PAPIAS,</hi> a meere Fabler: ſo that all the manie Witneſſes, which our Adverſaries heere alleadge for this his beeing at <hi>ROME,</hi> reſolue in one, and are but one in ſubſtance: for they all haue it but from him; and ſo this prooveth the laſt reſolution of the matter, <hi>PA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PIAS</hi> a fabulous Tale-teller related ſo. Ergo. Nay, <hi>BA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RONIVS</hi> in his Catalogue of his Authors for this For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, goeth no higher.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:9280:34"/>Againe, that great confuſion of <hi>BABEL</hi> woulde bee headilie adverted vnto, where ſcarce one vnderſtandeth anothers Language heere. Mee thinkes it ſtrange, howe they all, at leaſt in common, agreeing in the generall, that <hi>PETER</hi> was at <hi>ROME,</hi> ſhould ſo vniverſallie varie in everie circumſtance, as about the time of his going thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſome ſtanding for one yeare, and ſome for another. Truelie, all theſe cannot ſtand and ſubſiſt together, the firſt, the ſecond, the ſixt, or ſeaventh, the thirtienth of <hi>CLAVDIVS,</hi> &amp;c. Againe, about the place from whence hee went thither; nowe from <hi>HIERVSALEM,</hi> and nowe from <hi>ANTIOCH.</hi> Againe, about that conflict with <hi>SIMON MAGVS,</hi> which they make the ende of his going thither. Certes, <hi>omnia hîc</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp; fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſa:</hi> wherefore, as this alleadged ende of his going is but a Fable, his going it ſelfe may juſtlie ſeeme to bee but fabulous.</p>
               <p>Let mee poſe our Adverſaries heere a little: Why is not this <hi>SIMON'S</hi> oppoſing of <hi>PETER</hi> mentioned, as wee ſee the wickedneſſe of <hi>ELYMAS</hi> the Sorcerer againſt Sainct <hi>PAVL?</hi> Or, I pray you, Was not <hi>PAVL</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble enough for the worke, who ſmote that Sorcerer with blindneſſe? But I ſhould but in vayne buſie my ſelfe here in this matter of <hi>SIMON MAGVS, ubi omnia ſcatent fabulis:</hi> nay, where our <hi>MIDIANITES mutuis ſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiunt vulneribus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, about the place, time, and qualitie of his death; yea, and about his buriall: and laſt, about his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, ſome ſtanding for <hi>CLEMENT,</hi> and ſome for <hi>LINVS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, what can wee laye holde on in ſo great vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintis? Where-vpon can wee appuy or reſt heere our Fayth? And yet, <hi>ſi Diis placet,</hi> this is <hi>rei ſumma &amp; caput, PETER'S</hi> beeing at <hi>ROME.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:9280:34"/>Queſtionleſſe, it is from hence, that <hi>BELLARMINE</hi> finding but ſo weake a foundation to builde the Popes headſhip vpon, as convinced in judgement, againſt the light of his conſcience, ſeeketh thus to ſhift off the matter, and betaketh him to this poſterne, <hi>nec requiri, nec ſufficere,</hi> that this is neyther requiſite nor ſufficient to make <hi>PETER</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>ROME, de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. which hee proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth by partes: The firſt, Becauſe thus <hi>PETER</hi> ſhould haue beene Biſhop of <hi>HIERVSALEM, CAESAREA,</hi> and ſo foorth of all thoſe places whither-to hee came. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Becauſe manie were Biſhops of <hi>ROME,</hi> who came never thither, as <hi>CLEMENT</hi> the fift, <hi>IOHN</hi> the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie-two, <hi>BENEDICT</hi> the twelft, <hi>CLEMENT</hi> the ſixt, and <hi>INNOCENTIVS</hi> the ſeaventh; which were ordayned Biſhops in <hi>FRANCE,</hi> and abode ſtill there.</p>
               <p>I would inquire of our Adverſaries, Why they fight ſo much for this, which according to their owne confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and conceſſion, can neyther ſerue the turne, nay, ix not ſo much as requiſite there-vnto? May it not juſtlie ſeeme that they are but ledde heere by the ſpirit of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradition?</p>
               <p>I leaue for the tyme to diſpute the matter, whether this bee requiſite or not, that one come to that place, yea, and reſide there, whereof hee is created Biſhop: for our Adverſaries thus imprudentlie wrong their owne cauſe of perſonall and locall Succeſſion, except a deſignation to a place bee to them for locall Succeſſion; and ſo an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Biſhop and an actuall bee with them for one and the ſame. Laſt, it is well, that PETER thus of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle turneth an irregulare Biſhop, and a patterne of <hi>non</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence.</p>
               <p>But to deale a little <hi>punctim,</hi> as wee haue done <hi>caeſim:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt Argument may bee drawne from the puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and committing of tymes, to this ſenſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:9280:35"/>If wee ſhall bee pleaſed to commit and collation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the firſt and the ſecond Chapters of Sainct PAUL to the GALATIANS, wee ſhall ſee PETER to haue kept in IEWRIE, and therea-bout, ſome eighteene yeares after CHRIST'S Paſſion, as is cleare out of Sainct PAUL his viſiting of him at HIERUSALEM ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie yeares after his converſion, and of his after rebuking of him to his face at ANTIOCH. Nowe, if wee ſhall adde to this number, the ſeaven yeares of his beeing at ANTIOCH, and the twentie-fiue yeares of his Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke at ROME, there ſhall aryſe the ſumme of fiftie yeares, or there-abouts. From hence it followeth, That PETER could not haue ſuffered Martyredome with PAUL, as the common tradition hath at ROME, the twelfth or thirteenth yeare of NERO: for it is moſte certaine by collationing of the ſacred and prophane ſtorie, that there ran but thirtie and ſeaven. yeares for the moſte, from CHRISTS Paſſion, to the verie ende of NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RO his Empyre. What ſhall bee done with theſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerarie yeares heere? Nay, though wee ſhould praecide and cut off heere thoſe ſeaven yeares of his abode at AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIOCH, leſt wee might ſeeme too ſtrict <hi>in putandis tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus,</hi> wee ſhall yet find <hi>hiatum multum,</hi> no little gulfe or diſtance.</p>
               <p>Truelie, <hi>hic haeret iis aqua,</hi> our Adverſaries cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie expede and extricate themſelues heere, <hi>vtut in omnes ſe vertant partes:</hi> wherefore <hi>expectandus iis ELIAS aliquis, aut</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>qui nodum hunc ſolvat, fortean vel ſecet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next roome, I might reaſon from that generall, yea, and vniverſall ſilence of the whole Scriptures heere; as where wee can finde nothing for his going thither, as wee doe for PAUL'S, nor of his beeing there. Certes, <hi>in ſummis fidei capitibus argumentum rectè procedit negativè.</hi> Now,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:9280:35"/>this is <hi>rei ſumma &amp; caput,</hi> PETER'S Biſhopricke at ROME, which our Adverſaries collect of his beeing there; and conclude from hence, as who can finde no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter warrands elſe: where-vpon it followeth, <hi>quod ſuper are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naceo fundamento omnis illa inſana ſubstructio exstructa ſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But of ſurpluſſage heere; the Scriptures furniſh vs ſtore of Arguments againſt this forgerie: for if <hi>PETER</hi> had beene at <hi>ROME,</hi> before <hi>PAVL'S</hi> comming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, either hee was negligent, or elſe his miniſtrie there was fruitleſſe, and ineffectuall: for <hi>PAVL</hi> telleth round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, That hee found the <hi>IEWES</hi> in common innorant of CHRIST altogether, and His Goſpell; as which they odiouſlie inſtyled by the name of a Sect; and ſuch a Sect, as generallie evill ſpoken of, <hi>Acts, Chap.</hi> 28. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22. Or doe wee thinke, that the <hi>IEWES</hi> at <hi>ROME</hi> would haue carried greater reverence to <hi>PAVL,</hi> than to their owne ordinarie Apoſtle, if ſo bee hee had beene there?</p>
               <p>Againe, the manie Epiſtles which <hi>PAVL</hi> wrote from <hi>ROME,</hi> wherein hee doth not ſo much as make the leaſt mention of <hi>PETER,</hi> whether in Salutation, or Valediction, argue to the full, that hee co-lived not with <hi>PAVL</hi> at <hi>ROME.</hi> Nay, <hi>PAVL'S</hi> complaint, That hee was left alone, and forſaken of all at his firſt compea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and his depoſition, that at the ſecond tyme <hi>LVKE</hi> onelie was with him; theſe joyntlie conſidered, ſerue to prooue, That <hi>PETER</hi> was not at <hi>ROME</hi> now with <hi>PAVL;</hi> except wee would brand him with this foule not of Apoſtaſie, or deſerting of <hi>PAVL</hi> in the common cauſe of CHRIST, and the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Againe, mee thinketh it ſtrange, how <hi>PETER,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting two Epiſtles to the diſperſed <hi>IEWES,</hi> in diverſe Countreyes, could ſo deeplie forget thoſe at <hi>ROME;</hi> as not the leaſt to mention them, if ſo bee they were his
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:9280:36"/>chiefe charge, and <hi>ROME</hi> it ſelfe the Seate of his Popedome.</p>
               <p>Laſt, were not this flat againſt that compact betwixt him and Sainct <hi>PAVL,</hi> That hee ſhould goe to the <hi>IEWES,</hi> and <hi>PAVL</hi> to the <hi>GENTILES;</hi> which the Fathers acknowledged as ſingularlie adminiſtred by GOD, as you may ſee out of Sainct <hi>HIEROME,</hi> on the ſecond Chapter to the <hi>GALATIANS;</hi> and which wee ſee done with vniforme conſent of the reſt of the Apoſtles? Howe could wee free Sainct <hi>PETER</hi> heere of faedifragie, if contrarie to that covenant, thus ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie made, hee ſhould not onelie haue preached vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the <hi>GENTILES,</hi> and as it were extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narlie, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or by the way, but turned their ordinarie Apoſtle; yea, not Apoſtle, but Biſhop, to the great praejudice of his Apoſtolicall authoritie: as who is reckoned with them <hi>Apostolorum primus,</hi> as who perhaps was firſt called to the Apoſtleſhip, though <hi>ANDREW</hi> was called prior to the Diſcipleſhip.</p>
               <p>But to winde vp this point, leſt I might ſeeme for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull of my promiſe in the beginning of this Treatiſe, and ſo ſeeme too deeplie drowned in this Meditation, let mee thus argue for the generall:</p>
               <p>That Religion whoſe foundation and maine ground is <hi>purus putus ſtochaſmus,</hi> a meere ſtochaſme, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee but ſtochaſticke, and conjecturall:</p>
               <p>But ſuch is the Popiſh Religion to day: for Sainct <hi>PETER'S</hi> Biſhopricke at <hi>ROME,</hi> and his beeing there, which is <hi>rei ſumma &amp; caput,</hi> is but an ylde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, and fooliſh conjecture; as I hope is cleare to the full, from this my deduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the matter:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:9280:36"/>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Popiſh Religion is but ſtochaſticke, and conjecturall.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, ſeeing this point <hi>non cadit ſub fidem, immo ne ſub ſenſum quidem,</hi> there can bee no certainlie in their Religion, to ſettle mens conſciences. Truelie, there is great neede heere of a well implicite Fayth.</p>
               <p>Laſt, I offer mee, <hi>ne quid deſit,</hi> to prooue this point by that conſtant and ordinarie practiſe with our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, even vnto this day.</p>
               <p>Is not this the nature and qualitie of their ſuffragant Biſhops, as that their ordinations are abſolute, <hi>abſolutae,</hi> or <hi>ſolutae forte &amp; diſſolutae?</hi> Thoſe who vnderſtand but the leaſt into this matter, know, that heere for common both theſe Succeſſions are found wanting, perſonall and locall: for <hi>ex trivio nomen arripitur &amp; inditur, non ſcrupuloſè inquiritur in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Eccleſiae,</hi> from whence my L. receiveth his name. Truelie, the inſtitution of theſe is but a meere hiſtrionicall and dramaticall action.</p>
               <p>Alwayes, leſt I ſhould ſeeme to father an vntrueth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, I muſt entreate your patience heere a little, that I may ſnew the forme and manner of the creation of theſe ſuffragant Biſhops: wherefore, thus take the matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>REVEREND. D. BOGVINTINVS, HOSTIENSIS,</hi> or <hi>CO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LONIENSIS,</hi> ſtandeth in neede of a ſuffragant, as who cannot doe all by himſelfe; nay, as with whoſe dignitie it cannot ſtand <hi>omnium vertices contrectare, inungere.</hi> Nowe, this Suffragant can not doe thoſe thinges, which my L. ſhould haue done by himſelfe, except hee bee inſtructed with power, and ſo created Biſhop: for <hi>non potest quis in alium conferre, transferre, quod ipſe prior non habeat:</hi> wherefore hee is created Biſhoppe of ſome Tranſmarine Church, or other, from whence hee may receiue the denomination, whereas in the whilſt they are altogether ignorant of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:9280:37"/>ſtate of that Church, yea, doe not ſo much as vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of the Vacancie of the Seate; as wee had with our ſelues in SCOT-LAND ſome Biſhops of <hi>ATHENS,</hi> for-ſooth.</p>
               <p>The Suffragant beeing thus created, leaſt hee ſhoulde ſeeme a <hi>non reſident, dat ſe in viam,</hi> hee betaketh him to his journey, to his Station, for-ſooth; but <hi>ad tertium aut quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ab urbe lapidem,</hi> ſome three or foure myles off of the Towne, one is ſummitted, and ſo <hi>per lucida intervalla</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, to ſhew him of the danger of the journey, of the great loſſe and pert the Church ſhoulde ſuſtayne thorowe his departure: in a word, and in effect, to recall him to my L. where-vpon hee returneth; and vpon his returne, is praefected over ſome of his Churches, as his Vicar and Suffragant, where hee attendeth my L. Mandements.</p>
               <p>Nowe, vvho ſeeth not, except a Borne-blinde, that there is neyther perſonall nor locall Succeſsion heere? And yet theſe are the Fathers of all thoſe other Biſhoppes with our Adverſaries to day; theſe are they <hi>qui generant tot Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coporum examina,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus I hope, <hi>niſi mea me hic destituat ſpes,</hi> I haue ſhowne to the full, That this ſo much noyſed Succeſſion, is not to bee found with our Adverſaries. Now, I come to the laſt thing I promiſed to prooue, to wit, That wee haue ſuch Succeſſion, as is neceſſarie and requiſite here.</p>
               <p>For the clearing of this point, you muſt heere headilie diſtinguiſh betwixt thoſe things which are eſſentiall in and to Succeſſion, and ſo are altogether, or ſimplie neceſſarie, and theſe which are but accidentarie, and ſo may bee prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or abſent without deſtruction of the ſubject. Nowe, there bee two of each ſort; of the firſt are <hi>Succeſsio Doctrinae,</hi> and <hi>Succeſsio Vocationis:</hi> for it is heere ſimplie, and altogether neceſſarie, <hi>vt ſuccedatur in doctrinam Apostolicam.</hi> And the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:9280:37"/>is no leſſe neceſſarie, <hi>ſucceſsio Vocationis:</hi> for <hi>quomodo praedicabunt niſi mittantur? nemo ſibi hunc honorem aſſumit,</hi> &amp;c. It hath ſtill proven a matter full of danger, to vſurpe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Functions. But as to thoſe other two, perſonall and locall Succeſſion; that is, that a perſon ſucceede to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in and to a certaine place, theſe are not eſſentiall, and ſimplie neceſſarie, as without which a Church and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie may bee, yea, and are <hi>de facto</hi> amongſt themſelues, as their new built and inſtituted Churches amongſt the IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DIANS may inſtruct to the full; and as I haue proven alreadie at large, yea, and beſides other probations, from the practiſe of the primitiue Church, where <hi>fiebat vocati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Laſt, giving that there were ſuch perſonall and locall Succeſſion with our Adverſaries, it were no leſſe ours: <hi>Communes enim fuimus poſſeſſores, licet deturbarint nos de communi poſſeſsione, adeoque non excidimus jure ad rem, licet ſoli vſurpare ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lint jus in rem: ſiquidem non magis haec ſunt Papae, quam Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum DEI, illius Idoli fuiſſe cenſendum est, quod in eo collocârat ANTIOCHVS Epiphanes, rectius Epimanes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:9280:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>XIX. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>IERVSALEM vvhich is Aboue, is Mother of vs all, <hi>Gal. Chap.</hi> 4. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 26: as to the Church of <hi>ROME,</hi> ſhee was for the beſt but a Siſter-Church, and collaterall; but nowe wee affirme her to bee heavilie affected and diſeaſed. It is true indeede, that the Biſhop of <hi>ROME</hi> was called in common with the reſt of the Patriarches, by the name of occumenicall Biſhop; as which all joyntlie and commonlie repraeſented <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Nay, wee deny not heere yet farther, that the Biſhop of <hi>ROME</hi> obtained at laſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a certaine Procathedrie, or preſeance, and this perhaps not onlie becauſe that <hi>ROME</hi> was <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> or <hi>Caput Imperii,</hi> the Imperiall Seate, or Seage; or yet becauſe it prooved a <hi>ZOAR,</hi> or place of refuge to them of the Eaſterne Church, during the <hi>ARRIAN</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but even becauſe of the fayth, as which kept then the Trueth in ſinceritie, where-as other Churches were more corrupted; But all this is ours: for, as <hi>POMPEY</hi> ſayde well, <hi>Non est in parietibus Respuplica:</hi> ſo, no more is the Church of <hi>ROME</hi> within her Walles.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is an evill collection, to gather, or conclude ſtraight an vniverſall Proſtaſie from a particular Procathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:9280:38"/>Nay, and albeit the Church of <hi>ROME</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged vnto exemplarlie, whilſt ſhee kept the Fayth in puritie and ſinceritie, followeth it from hence, that ſhee was either the Mother-Church, or the Catholicke Church, which were <hi>orbem vrbi includere?</hi> The Ancients indeede <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducebant Eccleſiam Romanam, ſed vt exemplum particulare,</hi> ſcilicet, during that ſpace of her puritie, <hi>ſed ne vel tum quidem vt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributum vniverſale,</hi> which our Papiſtes doe to daye. You know, that this is ordinarie with vs, whilſt anie differ ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, to appeale or provoke to the moſt famous Church where wee liue, as in <hi>FRANCE,</hi> appellation is for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon made to the Church of <hi>GENEVE;</hi> or yet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the cognition of the matter to ſome Tranſmarine Church: but ſhall anie inferre from hence, That by this appellation wee abjudge the name of a true Church from our ſelues, or yet ſingularlie adjudge this name to that Church, wherevnto wee appeale? Nay, laſt of all heere, <hi>Ab Eccleſia Romana,</hi> during that her flowriſhing age, <hi>ad ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diernam Papanam non est concludere: distant ac differunt haec du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> immane quantum, immo</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:9280:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>XX. MELETEMA.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Chiefe Prieſts and Elders of the People, where-as they could not except againſt <hi>Christ's</hi> works, or <hi>authoritatem factorum,</hi> they began to quarrell <hi>authoritatem faciendi,</hi> and ſo to quaeſtion Him, by what authoritie Hee did theſe things, and who gaue Him this authoritie, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.23. Thus it fareth with our Adverſaries, or theſe our new <hi>Phariſees,</hi> to day, ſince they can not except againſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the doctrine which wee teach, leſt elſe they ſhould haue nothing at all to holde their poore bewitched people in hand, they muſt needs except here, and quarrell <hi>authoritatem</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and ſo ſquabble about our authoritie in Teaching, if not authoritie of Doctrine: wherefore let vs giue this to their ſo great and preſſing neceſſitie.</p>
               <p>There is one of our Men, no leſſe truelie in Digna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than Place, vvho hath latelie written moſt learnedlie in defence of our CALLING; vvhere-at I can not heare of anie amongſt our Adverſaries, vvho hath ſo much as ſnatched as yet but lyke a Dog leaping at NILVS: ſo that I graunt this to bee but a ſuperfluous labour on my part, vvhere-in but <hi>benè actum malè ago:</hi> yet I can not but looke for a charitable conſtruction: <hi>voluntas quum ſit actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num menſura;</hi> and that it may bee permitted to thoſe, <hi>qui prae tenui peculio vitulum vivum divis minus eluſtrare poſſunt, vel taurum è farina fingere;</hi> yea, and as who could not bee alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether heere <hi>muet,</hi> being ſo deicticallie pointed at, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the greater part in common, but at leaſt ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage taken by the Adverſarie vpon my ſilence againſt my ſelfe, though not to the leaſt praejudice to the errand or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:9280:39"/>cauſe, or yet derogation to the credit of the Miniſtrie with vs, through my weake ſides: wherefore, gentle Reader, giue to neceſſitie whatſoever thou findeſt heere done; and vouchſafe at leaſt thy beſt countenance, which is grace enough againſt all diſgrace I feare theſe whatſoever my paines ſhall incurre with the enemie, yea, or bee lyable vnto: for if thou pardon my praeſumption, and accept of this my meane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, thou ſhalt perhaps incourage mee to ſome greater attempt: what well done, giue GOD the praiſe; and where I haue taken the paines, reape thou the profit: what thou findeſt amiſſe, <hi>corrigi ac ſanari poſſe ne despera:</hi> as who, <hi>aliis vt proſim, veritatis Diſcipulus eſſe malim, quam, aliis dùm prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim, erroris Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <salute>VIVE. VALE.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:9280:40"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>Pag.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>lin.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>for</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">
                        <hi>reade</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>Margent,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>inſignari,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>inſigniri.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>Ibidem.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Meletemata,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>qui Meletemata.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>periet,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>pereat.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>appeare,</cell>
                     <cell>appeareth.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>quod,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>quos.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                     <cell>eſtate,</cell>
                     <cell>eſtates.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                     <cell>whiles,</cell>
                     <cell>whiles as.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>videri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>videſis.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Papista,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Papiſſa.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>ſolelie,</cell>
                     <cell>ſolly.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>Sainct,</cell>
                     <cell>Saincts.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chryſostomo,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Quarto.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>ao,</cell>
                     <cell>to.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>word,</cell>
                     <cell>words.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>thing,</cell>
                     <cell>things.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                     <cell>ſolelie,</cell>
                     <cell>ſolly.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>abſolutelie,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>abſolutae.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>65</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>defuerant,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>defuerunt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>not,</cell>
                     <cell>note.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>certainlie,</cell>
                     <cell>certaintie.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ibid.</cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Boguintinus,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Boguntinus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Item, in ſome places of this Treatiſe, for pretend, <hi>reade</hi> pertend.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
